Recording in progress.
Good evening, ladies and gentlemen. I
would like to call the May 11th meeting
of the governing body to order and ask
the clerk to take roll, please.
Dr. Aldrich. Present. Mayor Collins.
>> Here.
Dr. Emmons. Here. Mr. Escobel. Here. Mr.
Layborn. Present. Mr. Moody. Here. Dr.
Renny. Present. Mr. Seagrave.
Mr. White. Present. Mr. Wolfe. Here. One
member is absent. We do have a quorum.
Would you please join me in the pledge
of allegiance?
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the
United States of America, and to the
republic for which it stands, one nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
Madam Clerk, before we get started, I
understand there was uh some media that
talked about a moratorium on data
centers would be discussed this evening.
Um
our policy or our our process is it's
going to be read into the record tonight
and referred to the finance or excuse
me, the public services committee, which
will meet next Monday, and there will be
no discussion on that topic tonight. So,
if you're here to talk about it, that's
I apologize that the media got that
wrong.
Um we'll be talking about it next
Monday, and then a week from then, 2
weeks from today, will be the uh the
first time this governing body will take
that issue on and be able to talk about
it.
Next item, please.
Number four, consent agenda. All agenda
items listed with the designation of CA
are considered to be routine items by
the governing body and will be enacted
by one motion. There will be no separate
discussion on these items unless a
member of the governing body so requests
and support by two other members is
received. Any item removed from the
consent agenda will be considered in its
normal sequence on the agenda.
All right. Dr. Renny. Mr. Mayor,
I have a um potential conflict on item
item 30, so
I'm going to recuse myself from
discussion and voting on the consent
agenda.
Okay.
Dr. Emmons.
Uh Mr. Mayor, I'd like to remove uh 31A.
31A is the contract with Ryman
Corporation for the Story Boulevard
extension. Concur. Concur.
All right, that item has been removed
and will be considered in its normal
sequence on the agenda.
Mr. Leybourne.
Mr. Mayor, number 23.
Concur. 23 is being is referred to
committee, so it's not It can't It can't
>> Now, Mr. Mayor, It can't be By our
rules, cannot be
removed from the agenda. And which are
the rules? Where can I reference them?
Madam Clerk.
Mr. Mayor, through you, there is an
ordinance that outlines the consent
agenda regulations. I don't have it in
front of me at the moment, um but
generally we wouldn't have discussion on
this item anyway. It would just be read
into the record.
Mr. Mayor, that's what I'm requesting is
that be read into the record. There's
great interest in this
particular matter, and I think that it's
important that the
public, and particularly the people that
are interested in it, understand that it
will be coming before committee, and
then back uh
eventually to the council. Mr.
Leybourne, while we can't do that, I can
on item number 23 says approving the
budget of the Cheyenne Regional Airport
Board for the fiscal year beginning July
1st, 2026, and ending June 30th, 2027.
And I'm um referring that item to the
Finance Committee.
Thank you.
>> You're welcome. I also want Oh, yes,
sir.
Item number 30A.
Item 30A, okay.
Concur. Concur.
Dr. Rennie, you can come back in.
Mr. White.
Oh, sorry.
Okay. Are there any other items that
governing body would like to remove from
the consent agenda? Uh Dr. Rennie, the
30A has been removed, so it's not on the
consent agenda.
All right, hearing none, um I would
entertain a motion. So moved. Second.
That was Mr. Escobel.
And Mr. White.
All those in favor of the consent agenda
with item 31A and 30A removed, please
signify by saying I. I. Those opposed?
All right, the consent agenda is
approved with 31A and 30A being removed.
Um they'll be considered in their normal
sequence on the agenda.
Number six, public hearing for a
microbrewery permit application filed
with the city clerk's office for Yeager
Hund Brewing LLC doing business as
Yeager Hund Brewing, 3521 East
Lincolnway, Cheyenne, Wyoming.
All right.
Good evening.
Good evening. I'm uh Fred Hirsch, owner
of A. Yeager Hund.
Fred, can I have you to pull that
microphone down so people can hear you a
little better? There you go.
>> Thank you. Fred, you said? Yes. Welcome.
Can you tell us a little bit about what
your plans are? Uh we're constructing a
tap room brewery uh on the east side of
town in the Cheyenne
uh shopping center with Murdoch's and uh
Sportsman's Warehouse.
>> Yes, Cheyenne Plaza. Welcome. That'll be
awesome. Thank you. Anybody on the
governing body have a question for
um the applicant for this microbrewery
application? Mr. Mayor. Mr. Escobar. Can
you give us a little background uh what
the meaning of the name is or what type
of beers? Uh Yeager Hund is a a German
translation of the words hunting hound.
Uh our our brewery will be producing um
about 50% lager beers, all craft brewed,
all made with uh
uh
raw ingredients, uh barley, hops, uh
yeast, um just through normal brewing
processes like other craft breweries in
town. Uh we will not have any other
beverages other than our own that are
produced on site.
Um
and
we have a small tap room that has an
occupancy of about 100 people. So. Any
food service, sir?
No, sir. We will have snack options um
that will be purch- purchased third
party. We may have partnerships with our
our neighbors Durbar Indian restaurant.
And we may have a small bar menu that
they will produce the food on site at
their restaurant and bring it over to
our our brewery.
A marriage made in heaven. Yes, sir. I
love that. Thank you.
Anybody else from the governing body?
Good luck, sir. Thank you. How about
anybody else in the audience would like
to speak to the application for a
microbrewery permit?
All right, hearing none. It Last
comments from the council?
Hearing none, this public purpose has
been or the purpose of the public
hearing has been met. We'll sign this
item to the finance committee.
Number seven, ordinance third reading
amending section 13.20.050,
general prohibitions and section
13.20.070,
local [snorts] limits of chapter 13.20,
wastewater treatment and disposal of the
code of the city of Cheyenne, Wyoming,
to revise local discharge limits and
related provisions in compliance with
NPDES and WPDES permit requirements. All
right, we have an ordinance before us on
our third and final reading
that limits so I guess we work with DEQ
and EPA on the limits that can be
discharged into our system. Is there
anybody in the audience who would like
to speak to that?
Hearing none, Dr. Rennie.
Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
Public Service Committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I would
so move. Second. Seconded by Dr.
Aldridge. Mr. Mayor. Uh yes, sir. I
would move to postpone until the May
26th, 2026 meeting of the governing
body. Second.
It's been moved to postpone until May
26th by Dr. Rennie, seconded by Dr.
Aldridge. The reason for the
postponement is for this ordinance to
catch up with the
the public comment period for the EPA or
DEQ, whichever it is that is going on.
So, we'll go out to the audience to see
if anybody in the audience wants to
speak to the postponement.
How about from the governing body?
Hearing none, all those in favor, please
signify by saying aye. Aye. Those
opposed?
The ordinance is is postponed until May
26th.
Number eight, ordinance third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located south of
I-80, east of Southwest Drive, from
County LI Light Industrial, AG
Agricultural, and AR Agricultural
Residential to LI Light Industrial.
All right, [snorts] this is a zone
change for
uh to change the land to Light
Industrial from land that was annexed
actually in 2015. Is there anybody in
the audience who'd like to speak to the
the zone change before us?
If you'd like to come forward here,
please. Well, I just got a question, but
I'll talk to
Okay, you got to turn the the microphone
on.
>> [laughter]
>> You got that? I I'm going to try here.
All right, bring that microphone down
and introduce yourself, please. My
name's John Niles. John, welcome.
Resident.
Thank you. Uh question I have is is
there someone or an entity that's
looking to purchase or uh
do something with the land that's
proposed to be annexed?
Uh
Seth or Connor or does anybody have any
idea if there has been a It's already
been annexed. Uh was annexed It was
annexed in 20 15.
>> sorry, change I'm I I haven't spoke to
change the zoning.
>> Understood.
Seth, do we have any any idea on the the
the purpose?
Mr. Chair, um since you called me up,
I'm Seth Lloyd. I'm with the Planning
and Development Department. Um we do
have the applicant in the room, so he
might be able to better describe the
purpose of the zone change. Um there are
various uses that are allowed in the LI
zone that are not allowed in the current
zone district. Um in discussions with
the applicant, various options have been
brought forward, so we're not certain as
to what the end proposed use would be.
Um so there's various but there's
various uses in the LI zone, so I can't
speak any further than that um because I
am I'm certain myself.
Thank you.
Do anybody else want to speak to this?
Thank you, sir.
Mr. Sears, welcome.
Mayor, members of council, at this time
we don't have a particular uh purchase
option on the table, but we are trying
to accommodate the LI zoning that is
surrounding that area, so it conforms
with the uh total area at that point.
It's removing the AG and the AR to make
it LI as we had three separate on the
property.
Thank you.
Hope that answers your question, sir.
Anybody else in the audience?
All right, hearing none. Dr. Renne, may
we have a motion, please?
Mr. Mayor, the recommendation Public
Service Committee is to approve on third
and final reading, and I would so move.
Second. Seconded by Mr. Wolfe.
Comments from members of the governing
body on the ordinance?
I hear none. Madam Clerk, would you take
the the vote, please?
Mr. Wolfe.
I.
Dr. Aldridge. I. Mayor Collins.
>> Yes. Dr. Emmons. Yes. Mr. Escobel. I.
Mr. Laybourn. I. Mr. Moody. I. Dr.
Renne. Yes. Mr. White. Yes.
This ordinance is approved on third and
final reading.
Number nine, ordinance third reading
pursuant to section 2.2.2 planned
development regulating plan or
development master plan and section
5.6.2 PUD planned unit development
district of the unified development code
amending ordinance number 4524 by
modifying certain standards of the
adopted district plan planning unit
development PUD for Sweet Grass located
southeast of the intersection of College
Drive and Avenue C.
All right, we have a request for a
change to the PUD, which is basically
the zoning for this area, just a
different way of saying it. Um
anybody in the audience want to speak to
that?
Mr. Palmer, welcome.
Good afternoon, Mr. Mayor, members of
council. Casey Palmer, Palmer Land
Planning agent for the applicant.
Um I don't have anything particular to
add to the last meeting. If you
remember, this was voted for
unanimously.
Uh the idea here is to to create a
45-acre community park parcel, dividing
it off from the larger parcel, so that
we can hopefully over the next year get
some park facilities built at
Sweetgrass. I'd be happy to address any
questions you might have.
Any questions for the applicant? Doctor
Go ahead.
Thank you, Mr. Mayor, through you. Um
how long do you anticipate it will take
you to actually build
a facility that you're going to use
there?
Casey?
>> Uh Mr. Mayor, through you. Um this So,
this is a community park. This is
dedicated to the city. So, in 2018 when
we created the initial PUD, uh
60 acres was required to be dedicated to
the city. In our conversations with both
the city and a private recreation
developer, uh the city like to maintain
a 45-acre park, about size of Holiday
Park. Um and there is an opportunity to
bring additional private recreation to
the parcel, but the way that it's
divided and the way the PUD is written,
Mr. Bloom said, you know, that this
clearly is a major amendment, so that's
why it's before you this evening. Uh I
have been talking with the Greenway and
Parks planner about the minimum
improvements that they're able to do at
this time. We have a fund set up at
Sweetgrass with uh some funds in it to
contribute to those improvements. Um
technically, it's the the city's
responsibility to develop this, but
we're excited for the neighborhood to uh
kind of make it a public-private
partnership. So, there'll be some
private funds going to those
improvements. And like I said, I as soon
as we can sort of get things going on
the the public side with the um Parks
and Recreation Department on on what
they're able to contribute, um we have a
couple different sources that we'd like
to make sure we're contributing to get a
a few more improvements in in term.
I have a follow-up.
>> Dr. Emmons.
Thank you, Mr. Mayor. So, I always like
to know the whys of things. So, why is
it you decided to do this rather than to
let the city
uh
maintain control of that whole piece?
Um I think that that's a little bit
complicated as you may remember from
committee. Um
the Parks Department is pretty highly
burdened right now. They have a lot of
lands to maintain, a lot of parks to
maintain. Um
initially, we were approached by this
private recreation developer and they
said, "We'd like to be right next to the
park." And we said, "Well, that is
technically um city land that's supposed
to be dedicated to the city uh for them
to develop." And so, you know, our next
conversation was with the Parks
Department about how do you feel about
this? Um and because 45 acres is the
appropriate size for a community park,
they said, "You know, we have no
opposition to to them developing this
remainder, about 28 acres remainder, um
and and then we'll go ahead and move
forward with the 45." So, it it sort of
worked for everybody.
Mr. Mayor, one more follow-up.
>> Dr. Emmons. So, an
developer approached you, not the city
approaching you. Is that correct?
>> Uh that is correct. We We reached out to
the Parks Department about whether they
would be amenable to this, and the
answer was
we we'd be we'd prefer it. Okay. Thank
you. And Dr. Emmons, I can tell you when
I was asked about this, we went to uh
Mr. Sanchez and his team to ask. And
what they shared with us is uh
the park that the ideal size park in
this area would be around 45 acres. And
one of the challenges is if the city
owns property, if we want to get rid of
it, we have to surplus it. And so, um
you know, if if they really do really
want to build uh recreation there, then
um they would be in a position to do
that. We might not be in that same
position. Thank you.
Anybody else? Doctor
Aldridge.
Yeah, thank you, Mayor Collins, for you.
I think I just want to make sure that
I'm understanding this correctly that
um the 45 acres would be city property.
The
whatever facility would be a private
entity that owned it. So, anyone that
would be wanting to use it from within
the community would be paying it some
sort of a membership fee or some sort of
a fee to utilize it. It would not be
free to the public um, necessarily.
Uh,
Mr. Mayor, through you, I I'm not party
to those discussions. I know they have
approached Parks Department. I the they
have told me that they would they they
would be willing and interested in
offering some sort of a benefit to the
Sweetgrass residents. So, it would be
private to that neighborhood. Obviously,
that doesn't include all of the ward or
all of the city. Uh, regardless of that
fact, I mean, we've been, you know, had
lots of neighbors that were promised by
their realtors that they would have a
park there. And as of yet, the city has
to imp- you know, has yet to improve it.
Uh, and so, what we've been working on
is trying to facilitate how do we sort
of work together with the city to make
sure that we get some of those
improvements made. Um, the promise to
dedicate this amount of acreage, as you
can imagine, it it's a pretty
substantial amount of acreage. The
city's paid
millions of dollars for similar acreage
for for parklands. And so, uh, I think,
you know, the fact that the land was
promised to be dedicated and the fact
that it was promised to be developed by
the city is we want to work with the
city to be a good partner and to make
that happen. And and despite not being
required to contribute to those
improvements, um,
yeah, Sweetgrass is is willing to sort
of move it move it forward. Um, but the
only way to do that is to create this
this PUD amendment. And then, you'll
see, um, at the next round of submittals
here, so in about a month or so, a plat
coming forward that would it, you know,
facilitate then that that dedication,
that private development. I can't speak
to whether the private development will
ac- ever happen, right? So, we were
approached by a potential developer of
that land. So, um, it still would be in
a recreation use. It's it's locked in
that as a zoning. So, we would have to
come you know, come back before this
body if we wanted to change the use to
something else um other than you know,
as the the the other portions of the
amendment about zone changes are are
allowed uh with this amendment, too.
But,
the idea here is not to you know,
there's no smoke and mirrors. There
Nobody's trying to sort of you know,
leverage anything. Um I think the city
would like to you know, make some of
those improvements and Wegmans would
like to provide their residents with
that city park that was planned and
required at the outset. So, that's
that's all we're trying to do here. Mr.
Palmer, maybe maybe there's some
confusion. The 45 acres that the city
will own will still be a free park owned
and operated by the city. What what
we're talking about is the land that um
that the owner of the property wants to
donate to a private um group would be um
would be a private venture, right? So,
we we're still going to have 45 acres of
free park for from the city's
perspective. That is correct, Mr.
>> Okay. Just making sure I understood.
Thank you.
Anybody else in the governing body for
the applicant?
Thank you, Casey. Anybody else in the
audience?
Mr. Bloom, did you
Mayor, members of council, Charles
Bloom, planning and develop development
director. I just wanted to uh clarify a
couple things that have transpired over
the the course of this this item being
considered. Um there's been a lot of
discussion regarding the maintenance and
CRE's um anticipated maintenance for
this this park site if developed at 45
acres or developed at a larger area.
They have indicated throughout that yes,
the comprehensive plan does identify
that 45 acres is a target acreage for
community park, and they're fine with
something meeting that target acreage.
However, if this was the larger park
site, the 67 acres as presently
proposed, they'd go out there and
maintain that all day long. Um the
biggest cost to them is mobilization
when they
have to move equipment from one site to
the other. That's why they like to have
their park areas grouped.
There is a related annexation agreement
that framed the annexation of the
Sweetgrass development. In the
annexation agreement, it did talk a lot
about parks. It talked about what a park
um impact fee would be for this area. It
set a payment schedule up. Um and that's
been saved in a specific account that's
for park improvements.
Um it also did clarify that in the event
that parkland was dedicated for public
use, that it would be ideally one large
park area, which is being accomplished
with this development, whether or not
this item does um pass.
One thing I should know is presently
that land is not owned by the city right
now. It is still owned by the uh
initial developer. They own that and
their ultimate goal would be to dedicate
that as parkland. Um that's per the
annexation agreement as called out for
in the
uh development um this planned unit
development.
I would like to note that this is an
item that we have been considering in
our department for quite an extended
period of time. I believe this is the
fifth or sixth time that we have
revisited the Sweetgrass PUD and done
amendments um over the course of time.
A lot of the uh benefits of the planned
unit development uh
that are remaining
um
are geared specifically towards the
commercial development and the design
materials and design standards in that
commercial development that is still
developing. A lot of the items that were
initially incorporated in the planned
unit development such as lot sizes, lot
coverage, uh street standards, those
types of items. A lot of those could be
uh
could be addressed
administratively or they've been
addressed with unified development code
changes that we've had over the course
of the year.
Um so, if there is any apprehension to
making this uh change um in zoning, um
it it could be uh it'd be a good
question for the applicant as to what
are the benefits that they are seeing by
continuing to have this planned unit
development.
Um one of our biggest uh courses of
action in the planning world is to try
to make our processes and our reviews a
lot more efficient. Planned unit
developments,
although they do serve uh time and and
place,
um they really create predictability and
their goal is to
uh create uh something that has
uh a little bit of a this for that. Um
they'll be given some flexibility while
the public is given another uh benefit,
trying to balance those needs.
Um
>> [clears throat]
>> Planned unit developments uh do serve a
great purpose when they're initially
done. However, as they continue to last
over the years,
uh details get missed, they can become
confusing, um and they can be
challenging to enforce. So, in any
instance where we can find a way to
either have them sunset or zone them to
straight zoning and still accomplish the
end result, um we will try to look for
ways to do that. Um we do believe that
in this case, there could be ways that
uh this development could be facilitated
through straight zoning. Um but again,
um if there's specific details other
than the uh
park area change, um I would ask the
applicant to um provide information on
what the the benefits of remaining in
the PUD are.
>> [snorts]
>> Thank you, Charles.
Dr. Aldridge. Uh Mayor Collins, to you.
So,
I
the land is still in the owner's name,
although it's been
set aside
or dedicated for park usage, recreation
uses usage.
If the 66 acres were to come
to the city,
um and then we decided that we only
wanted to do a 45-acre park,
um
at that point in time,
would we have the flexibility to uh take
the additional land and uh
develop it ourselves for recreational
purposes or to sell it to a private
company to develop for recreation?
Charles, I don't know if you're the
right person to answer that question.
Does the PUD or or Casey, does it does
it contemplate
um
once we have the property what we could
do with it?
Mayor, through you to members of the
council, um the PUD doesn't contemplate
that, but it would fall directly on
state statute where we would have to put
that property out to public bid um for
any other person to develop, so there'd
be no guarantee as to who the bidder
would be. So, there's no deed
restriction that it'd have to be for
recreational use when we take it over
that you're aware of?
Mayor, members of the council, I'm not
aware of a deed uh restriction that is a
condition of the planned unit
development. I would defer that to the
applicant if he knows any different on
that item. Your assistant Seth is
walking up. Maybe he has some other
Good evening, Seth. Mr. Mayor, Seth
White the Planning and Development
Department. Um there's a couple of
things going on here. One is the PUD has
a zone and there's multiple little zones
throughout the PUD. One's uh
uh uh
like a entertainment center or something
like that. Others are high density
residential, low density residential.
This land is zoned park and recreation.
So, it's not really a deed restriction
so much as it is the zoning of this land
to be recreational.
There is a currently in the PUD, this is
currently in the PUD, an allowance that
if it's not dedicated to the city, it
can be used for housing. Um so, right
now in the PUD, if the city said we only
want 45 acres and the developer took on
the remaining 20 acres,
the developer could do that for housing
right now as the PUD is currently
written. Um
the a proposed amendment includes some
language that would restrict that to uh
make sure that we can include recreation
clearly. Um but that's kind of what it
is. It's a zone within the PUD, not so
much a deed restriction.
Um so, that is there and it would be
restricted if the city took control of
that land and then surplussed it or
whatever, it would be restricted by its
zoning within the PUD to recreation or
housing. Thank you, sir. Dr. Aldern, can
I help help you?
>> Yeah, so I just want to
I because I think that this becomes very
convoluted and I have some constituents,
I represent Sweetgrass,
um as do my colleagues also from Ward 3,
and there's been a real feeling by some
of those residents that it's been a real
bait and switch out there. They were
promised some things when that PUD was
put together, such as a community center
that now has been turned into a retail
area and rented out for office spaces
and things that um they have to
uh are no longer able to rent for events
and things like that that they thought
was going to happen. Some of them
thought or were told there was going to
be a golf course at one point. Um I
mean, there's been all sorts of
things and I know that people say things
when they're trying to sell properties
and
um
things like that happen, but I'm just
I'm really hesitant to give the leniency
um
when this PUD was established
um and that this was a concession that
we were flexible on something else
because they were going to set aside 66
acres for recreation. And now they're
saying, "Well,
maybe you really only need 45 acres and
we could then sell this property to a
recreational private entity to you know,
that would be co-located with this
park." Um
I really feel like that's part of the
um
benefit, if you will, or part of the
concession that was made when this PUD
was done that is really a city would be
a city asset that we're agreeing to
basically
allow them to retain those 22 acres and
sell it off to a private entity where
the general public would not have access
to that property. So, I am not um
that's my biggest concern. I just want
to make sure that I clearly understand
that that's really what's happening
here.
Anyone else in the audience?
Tina.
Welcome. We have Charles Miller
online.
Mr. Miller.
Go ahead, Mr. Miller.
Can you hear me? We can.
Mr. Miller, are you there?
Uh I'm sorry. Give me just a second
here. My Zoom is messing me up.
Mr. Miller, if you're not ready, we can
come back to you. Oh, okay. Okay, that'd
be great. Thank you. Sure.
Welcome.
Jim Cherol.
Ward 1. Um
through you, Mayor.
>> [snorts]
>> Uh I support where you're where you're
going with that, uh Dr. Aldridge. Um but
in the interest of what what did you say
or they they dedicated it back what 2015
or something?
Is when they were going to give the park
to them?
Um, I'm not sure we
>> When was the land
proposed to give to the to the city? The
68 acres. Uh, originally
>> Mr. Palmer, introduce yourself, please.
>> Casey Palmer, Palmer Land Planning. Um,
it was initially in the 2016 annexation
agreement and then codified in the 2018
PUD amendment. Um,
So, there's it hasn't hasn't been
formally Just in the interest for the
folks that are out there for Sweetgrass
that, you know, give them a park.
They've been waiting for 10 years. I
agree with where you're going on it, but
I think we need to go and check with
state statute. You know, if you give me
a gift, I can't go and cut off that part
of that gift and sell it for another
purpose. It'd be nice, but if it was
zoned for either we got to take the
whole 68 acres and not approve them for
that separate zoning or let's just go
ahead and pass this now and allow them
to,
you know, take that that other portion
and give the residents that 45-acre
park, which I've already said we're
pretty well tasked as far as
the parks department. That 45 is like
about a limit, so that would be my
recommendation for those interests
>> And Jim, I don't think I don't think
we're tasked to the point where we can't
manage more than that, but what we found
is the ideal size for a regional park
like that is 45 acres. We can put all
the amenities in there and maximize the
resources of the department. Um, you
know, that that's what the director of
that department has asked for.
Um, and I would just share with you, um,
we have the land for Quail Hollow Park,
which would serve the Sweetgrass area on
the eastern part of town and that
subdivision is almost built out now.
Um, and we have some other park areas
that we've acquired over the last few
years knowing that there'll be a time in
the future where those parks would be
necessary that are older neighborhoods
that probably would move forward uh this
one, but
um
yeah.
Okay. Thank you, Jim. All right, thank
you guys.
All right, Mr. Miller.
Go ahead, Mr. Miller.
Can you hear me?
Yes, Mr. Miller, we can hear you.
All right, give me just a second here.
Tina, let's go on to somebody else. Mr.
Miller's not ready.
Oh, sorry about that.
Okay. Is there anybody else in the
audience wants to speak?
Mr. Palma.
Mr. Mayor, Casey Palma again, Palma Land
Planning. I just wanted to clarify uh to
I appreciate uh Councilman Andres's
entrepreneurial spirit, but the PUD does
say that it should be I mean, I can read
it word for word if you want, but the
parcel is intended to be dedicated
primarily for a community park and other
recreational uses
uh to be to the city of Cheyenne to be
developed by the city as a public park
to serve the residents of South
Cheyenne. So, that I mean, that's just
the clear code language. So, I I
I'm not an attorney, but I think that
that was always the intent, that is
still the intent. 45 acres is the
appropriate size.
Um and I
I realize there's a lot of issues around
parks and cities and realtors and
everything else, but uh I do think what
we're trying to do here is to make the
neighborhood better, to be able to build
a community park to serve all of South
Cheyenne.
And I, you know,
really the private recreation developer
is a totally side issue. It's not really
relevant to what we're doing here, which
is is trying to move the ball forward on
giving the city 45 acres so that that
can be developed as a private park. And
as I mentioned, um not putting the
burden entirely on the city to build
that park, but also contributing to
that. Uh the only other thing I would
note in regards to the PUD, I mean, I
staff does
recommend approval. Um there's no
criterion that we're asking to be waived
or varied here. Um so this was fully
recommended by staff.
Um but we Sweetgrass by far has more
open space than any development in the
city of Cheyenne. I can confidently say
that. Uh the plan is about 40% open
space and we've pretty well stuck to
that up to this point. So um there is
already a significant amount of public
and private open space, greenway
constructed by the developer. This
doesn't change any of that and it
doesn't change the plan moving forward.
All it does is facilitate that amendment
so that we can help the city develop
that 45 acres and that the residents can
then, you know, have some amenities
there. Um no promises were broken by
Sweetgrass in terms of what was promised
and what's being delivered. You can read
through the entire PUD and we could sit
down and talk more about it at a later
date. Um
I understand there being concerns. I
understand there being a lot of nuanced
issues going on, but I I really would
hope that uh you all and you know
hope that you all would see the logic
and the benefit that can be come from
this amendment and uh and vote in favor
of it this evening. So sorry to take
more of your time, but I just wanted to
get straight clarified that. All right,
Channel. Let's try him one more time.
>> [clears throat]
>> If he's ready, we'll go.
Mr. Miller, are you ready?
I am. Okay, let's go.
Um Mayor Collins, members of the
council, Charles Miller for the record.
I'm speaking to the request to amend the
Sweetgrass PUD specifically regarding
the community parkland dedication.
As we heard in the staff report and from
the applicant, there is a move to split
the promised 60-acre community park into
a 45-acre city parcel and a 28-acre
private parcel.
Um
as council Councilman Aldrich noted,
uh Aldrich noted, sorry. Uh many
residents in Sweetgrass already feel a
sense of bait and switch um regarding
the promises made at the outset of this
project. Um and by approving this
amendment, we are formally codifying
that reduction in public space.
Furthermore, I want to draw the
council's attention to subsection H,
which allows for a 25% change in land
use designation without triggering a
major amendment review.
While this still requires standard
zoning map amendment procedures, it
allows the developer to bypass the
rigorous major PUD amendment process,
lowering the threshold for altering the
master plan and removing the
predictability the community was
promised. I urge the council to reject
this amendment until the public is
provided with a guaranteed transparent
map showing exactly what this private
recreation entails and why the city is
settling for 15 fewer acres of public
parkland than originally promised. Thank
you.
All right, anybody else in the audience?
Hearing none,
we'll go to Dr. Ernie.
Mr. Mayor, there was no recommendation
from the public service committee.
However, for the sake of discussion, I
would move to approve on third and final
reading. Second.
That's it, Mr. Wolfe.
All right, comments from members of the
governing body. Dr. Ernie, did you have
comments, sir?
No, you know, I Mr. Mayor, I kind of
gone back and forth on this a little
bit. I did have
public service committee with
with our director of of
community rec and events and
um obviously 45 acres he thinks is the
ideal
is the ideal size of a regional park.
We've had a regional park um plan for
that area for a while and
I
I don't think if
although we could use all 67 68 acres,
um I think if we have the opportunity
for someone outside of us to build a
some kind of indoor facility, I think
that's an advantage to the community.
So, in the end I'm going to support
this.
Mr. White.
Uh Mr. Mayor, through you, uh
kind of just what the gentleman uh from
Ward 1 had indicated, 45 acres is still
a significant contribution
in the realm of a public park. I mean,
Holiday Park is a good size park. And
so, to have the size of something like
that out on the Sweetgrass property, I
think we're keeping in line with the
agreement from
8 years ago
and uh that it will significantly
benefit uh the Sweetgrass area. So, I'll
I'm completely in support of it.
Any other comments from members of the
government? Mr. Wolf. Um thank you, Mr.
Mayor, through you. Um I'm going to vote
uh in favor of this. Uh um
I think this this is
you know, there's not really a a lot of
complexity here, um
but it's one of those things I think
where
um
I come down on the side of needing to
trust the judgment, Mr. Mayor, of you
and your office and of uh
Director Sanchez and of uh
Director Bloom and uh his staff. Um
It is a big park, um and um
if they'll take the geese from Holiday
Park and from Lions Park, we'd be really
happy with that. So,
um
anyway, I'll be voting yes. Thank you.
Dr. Alge, do you have any other comment
now?
Uh no, Mayor Collins, I just um I
want to say that I have complete
um faith in our CRE department and that
um whatever size park they're given, I
know that uh Director Sanchez and his
team will um make sure it's taken well
care of. Um
my concern is always when we take things
that are meant for public use and then
make them restricted for only those who
are able to afford or be able to access
them. And just because we passed this
tonight does not mean that that park is
going to appear anytime soon because
there's just not the funding that's been
set aside for that. So, that empty lot
that 45 acres may continue to sit there
as 45 acres for quite a while. Um so,
um for that reason, I I am going to go
ahead and vote for this tonight, but um
I just want to definitely
uh say that um the folks in Sweetgrass
um
deserve to be heard and need to be
recognized, and I think the developers
should be put on notice that um we're
watching.
Any other comments?
I hear none. Madam Clerk, would you take
the vote, please?
Mr. White.
Yes. Mr. Wolf. I. Dr. Aldrich. Yes.
Mayor Collins.
>> Yes. Dr. Emmons. Yes. Mr. Escobel. I.
Mr. Laybourn.
Yes. [clears throat] Mr. Moody. I.
>> [snorts]
>> Dr. Renny. Yes.
The ordinance is approved on third and
final reading.
Number 10, ordinance second reading
amending enforcement and permitting
requirements related to oversized
vehicles and making conforming
amendments. All right, we have an
amendment to our recently passed
oversized vehicle ordinance. Is there
anybody here tonight to speak to that
change?
All right, hearing none. Mr. Escobel.
Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
Finance Committee is to approve on
second reading, and I so move.
>> Second. Seconded by Mr. White.
Comments from members of the governing
body.
Hearing none. All those in favor of the
ordinance on second reading, please
signify by saying I. I. Those opposed?
>> No. No. The ordinance is a passed uh
approved on second reading with Messrs.
Laybourn and Moody voting no.
Number 11, ordinance first reading
amending the and updating the solid
waste fee schedule in accordance with
section 8.44.010
of the municipal code of the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming and repealing
ordinance number 4621.
We'll refer this item to the finance
committee.
Number 12, ordinance first reading
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne changing the zoning
classification for land located
southwest of the intersection of HR
Ranch Road and Judy Lee Drive and
southeast of HR Ranch Road and Judy Lee
Drive from JL Ranch PUD planned unit
development to NR2 neighborhood
residential medium density. We'll send
this item to the public services
committee. Number 13, ordinance first
reading appropriating monies for the
city of Cheyenne, Wyoming for the
various purposes in conducting the
municipal government of of said city and
fixing the amount of the general and
special taxes as part of the revenue
required to meet the set appropriation
all for the fiscal year beginning July
1st, 2026 and ending June 30th, 2027.
We'll refer this item to the committee
of the whole. We don't We do committees
of the whole very often. They're going
to be next Wednesday 6:00 right here.
They'll be made up of all members of the
city council.
Number 14, ordinance first reading
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne changing the zoning
classification for land located in
Cheyenne Business Park and
Park in eastern Cheyenne along I-80 from
LI light industrial, HI heavy industrial
and CB community business to BP business
park. All right, we'll send this item to
the public services committee.
Number 15, ordinance first reading
approving and establishing revised water
and sewer rates, tap and system
development fees, administrative fees,
service charges and penalties and septic
and commercial waste dump rates as
recommended by the Board of Public
Utilities. This one will go to the
finance committee.
Number 16, ordinance first reading
imposing a temporary 12-month moratorium
on the establishment, construction or
conversion of any buildings or
structures for use as a data center
including any change of use to a data
center.
This item will go to the public services
committee.
Number 18, resolution amending the
future land use map of plan Cheyenne
changing the land use designation from
urban transition residential to mixed
use employment for property generally
located west of Round Top Road and
adjacent to Happy Jack Road and amending
the urban service boundary.
All right, we'll go out to the audience
on this.
Uh the committee though, I'll tell you
um
uh made a uh
a recommendation to move this to
September 28th, so it will follow with
the zoning and the annexation that uh
was approved uh here what is it a couple
weeks ago now. So, we'll go out to the
audience on the uh land use the future
land use plan. Anybody want to speak to
that?
Mr. White, welcome. How are you? Good.
Uh through you, Mr. Mayor, Michael
White.
I want to make sure I understand that
right cuz
that was one of the reasons I came
tonight since we postponed the
annexation and the zoning till the 14th.
So, my understanding is now this part is
going to go to the 28th of September. Is
that correct?
>> That is correct, sir. Thank you.
Anybody else?
All right, hearing none, I'll go out to
Dr. Rennie.
Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to adopt
and I would so move.
Thank you. Seconded by Mr. Wolfe. Mr.
Mayor. Dr. Rennie. I have moved to
commit this resolution to the public
services committee
and to until September 28th, 2026
governing body meeting. Second. Seconded
by Mr. White.
We'll go out to the audience on the
motion to uh refer this to the public
services committee and have them report
back on September 28th, 2026.
Anybody?
How about from the governing body?
Hearing that, all those in favor please
signify by saying aye. Aye. Those
opposed? This item um will be referred
back to the public services committee
until September 28th, 2026.
Next item is number 22 on page four.
Resolution approving the budget of the
Cheyenne Downtown Development Authority
for the fiscal year beginning July 1st,
2026 and ending June 30th, 2027.
All right. Well, glad to the audience.
Is there anybody in the audience that
wants to speak to the budget of the
Downtown Development Authority?
You don't have to say anything, Dave, if
you don't want to.
We're just happy to see you.
But, you're welcome to come, sir.
Mr. Mayor, through you. Um, Dave Tubner,
president, uh, board president of the
DDA. I just want to thank, uh, the
council for their ongoing support. Been
a tough tough couple of years for the
DDA.
Um, but through your guidance and
housing and support of staff, uh, we
really feel like we're on the right
trajectory. You will see a growth in
budget this year. Um, we're investing
in, uh,
things like the planter program we're
pretty excited about. Um,
in that that had always been a
year-over-year kind of new RFP kind of
investment.
In the last year, we put out an RFP and
found a regional grower that is growing
now specifically for the planters in the
downtown, uh, planting project. And
extended that to a three-year agreement
instead of year-over-year finding a new
contractor and a new partner in
relationship.
Um, and so that's an exciting investment
for us, um, we think to really beautify
these things in a consistent basis. Um,
also investing in, uh,
keeping them a little bit fresh in the
winter months also and exploring that
with the planter.
We're also investing in flags and
hardware and infrastructure and bulbs
and things like that that have
um
some council members have been very
passionate about and are appropriately
so um because some of the infrastructure
has just been
uh neglected or it's tough in Wyoming
weather. Um so we're investing in things
like that.
Um
so I appreciate I we can answer any
other questions as it relates to the
budget, but uh we're excited about um
the grant money that we're putting out
into the community. The private sector
is growing and there's a whole variety
of different projects that are accessing
our grant programs at a higher clip than
ever before. And so I we maybe have uh
stopped doing sponsor or events directly
and there's been a lot of talk about
that.
We also are trying to grow our
sponsorships uh dollars to encourage
events that are not executed by us, but
executed by people that are already
bringing crowds um and executing events
on a annual basis and not doing what we
do.
Um
so a little bit of growth in budget, but
we're we're paying attention to
infrastructure and long-term stability
and putting a lot of money back into the
private sector for
their redevelopment projects and those
are on an increase. So thank you for
your ongoing support. Dave, thanks to
you and all the board members uh for
your service to our downtown. And uh
anybody else in the audience want to
speak to uh
ask Tina. Who do you have? We have
Charles Miller. Mr. Miller.
Go ahead, Mr. Miller.
Can you hear me?
Yes, Mr. Miller, we can hear you.
Um
uh Mr. Mayor, members of the city
council, uh Charles Miller for the
record. Um I I just wanted to start off
by saying that if any of my uh numbers
are incorrect, uh please please let me
know. Um I'm trying to crunch a lot of
different numbers, so sometimes things
get a little bit messed up.
Um but I'm speaking tonight uh is this
is this item number 22? It is.
Um and regarding the fiscal year 2027
budget for the Downtown Development
Authority, specifically uh looking at
the proposed substitute.
While the substitute resolution
commendably reduces the total budget
from 1 million uh $52,800
to $1,022,800,
a forensic audit of the line items
reveals a highly unsustainable
structural deficit and overlapping
municipal inefficiencies.
Um I urge the council to carefully
examine three specific leverage points
before voting on this appropriation.
Um first is the aggressive depletion of
reserves.
Um even with the $30,000 reduction in
the substitute, this budget requires
drawing $434,190 directly from reserves
to fund basic operations.
Relying on nearly half a million dollars
in reserve capital to float a single
fiscal year is not sustainable fiscal
policy, especially when a significant
portion of the spending is directed
toward highly discretionary line items,
such as is it $87,000 for planters and
$75,000 for sponsorships?
Um
second, uh the
the uh the budget allocates $65,100
for independent office expenses
located outside the municipal building.
This includes $24,000 for rent and
$10,000 for cleaning.
However, the menu the memo explicitly
notes that the city has provided
physical office space and all associated
amenities at no cost to to the DDA since
March 2023.
Hey Charles, I'll just stop you for just
a second. I can share with you that if
we're successful in the six-penny and we
remodel this room or this building,
they'll have to leave for a while to
find office space and so they're
planning for the eventuality that we
might have to move everybody out of this
building and so they're making sure it's
in the budget just in case.
I'll let you continue, sir.
Okay, thank you. Um
You're actively choosing to drain
reserves to pay commercial rent when
municipal space was readily available.
Um
the justification for the DDA's
independent overhead falls apart when we
look at the city's existing burden
burden.
The city of Cheyenne is already
contributing approximately $290,900
to cover all DDA payroll, insurance, and
benefits.
Additionally, city staff continues to
provide support to DDA employees at no
cost. The DDA is functioning as a fully
subsidized municipal arm while spending
taxpayer reserves to simulate the
autonomy of a private entity.
Um in conclusion, uh before authorizing
this substitute budget, I ask the
council to audit the necessity of a
$65,100
independent office lease while the city
is already providing free support staff
and $290,900
in payroll subsidies. The DDA's mission
is to revitalize downtown, not to burn
through $434,190
in reserves to cover newly created
administrative overhead. Mr. Billy, your
time is up, sir. Thank you.
Anybody else?
Okay, hearing none. Mr. Escobel.
Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
Finance Committee is to adopt and I so
move.
>> Second.
Mr. White is the second. Mr. Escobel.
Mr. Mayor, I move to amend by substitute
dated May 5th, 2026.
Second.
Seconded by Mr. White. We'll go back out
to the audience.
Uh the substitute is to reduce the
budget by $30,000.
Um if you've ever done a budget,
sometimes you hide a an item in the
budget, and we know you guys are
discussing it, um and then uh you go
back later and erase it. Uh they hit it,
but it didn't get erased, and so uh it
inadvertently got into the budget,
overinflating it by $30,000. So, this is
just a an effort to what I would call a
scrivener's error and and and correct
that. Is there anybody in the audience
who wants to speak to that error?
How about from the governing body?
Hearing none, all those in favor, please
signify by saying aye. Aye. Those
opposed? Okay, we're back on the budget.
Uh uh
anybody else?
Yes.
Dr. Aldridge.
Mr. Collins, through you. I am uh
wondering um about the reserve, and I
don't know if someone can answer this or
not, but um I understand that
um
the
DDA itself does have a healthy reserve
currently.
There has been a request um by an
another outside user group uh made up of
downtown residents for that $500,000,
and I'm wondering if that $500,000
request can be accommodated
um
in this current budget.
Mr. Tubbs, can you maybe talk to us
about your spending of reserves and um
if you wouldn't mind, sir.
Mr. Mayor, through you.
Um
it's a good question. Uh
the reserves have been building for a
great number of years, and they've
always been kind of earmarked for a
large project, i.e., a grocery store,
some something that was mission
critical. Um
and they There is a recent request um
from uh Shine or Downtown First, um and
they have made a request of $500,000
of reserve funding.
We've never received anything like that,
didn't know it was coming. Um, we're in
support of that organization and the
important role that they play. Um, and
excited about the ignition that they're
making around the foundation. The
foundation has sat dormant for a variety
of years, and so there's some excitement
around that group's uh spearheading
that.
We've funded a few of their activities
in the past, and part of our budget
growth for sponsorship was to continue a
partnership with them. We don't fully
understand uh the request, um, nor do we
fully understand its legality of
transfer of something like that, because
it's never been done before.
Um, and so I've reached out to
Sam Galeotos, their chairman, and we
asked to have a group up and uh
understand a little bit more about the
request and where they're going as an
organization. They're listing us as a
partner. I think we want to be
supportive. There's There's a lot of
roles to play in the in the next 10
years of growth for downtown Cheyenne,
and I do think that they play a critical
one.
Uh dipping into uh
that reserve uh that's been preserved
has to be for an important strategic
purpose. Um, and I'm not suggesting they
don't have one. Um, we just don't know
enough, and so we thought we would group
up and have a little powwow between the
two teams and and and see if we can have
a deeper understanding. If something
like that materialized that felt like it
was important, it would come back as a
budget amendment. It wouldn't be
recognized in the current budget, um,
outside of some of the sponsorship ideas
we had
on a yearly basis uh to fund them like
we were already thinking about. That is
in the budget, but we don't really know
the the nature of the full request just
yet. Mr. Tuber, can you comment on the
400 and
thousand plus dollars that are going to
come out of your reserves for this
year's budget and how you're investing
those and I think maybe part of the
question I've heard twice now is
does that seem like the right thing to
do is to spend those reserves?
Maybe I'll let Sophia speak directly to
the budget and the reserve difference.
Like I said, we're
without the without the
we did forecast some of the move out
because we're unsure about the
the nature of the space, but we also
were exploring and were asked by the
community to explore and I think even
the council to explore our long-term
home. Um and whether or not it should be
housed and it had always been housed
outside and downtown and often in a
retail environment and there was an
expense to that. What a lot of people
don't remember or know is in the last
administration before you mayor,
there was a big change made and a
reduction of funding. It used to be
double I think what the city puts in in
regards to staff and those kind of
things. And there was also a change in
the mill levy that didn't allow for
administrative costs. And so when those
two things happened, this organization
was changed forever.
Visit Cheyenne picked it up and because
of that reduction, tried
tried and moved the organization forward
and then it came back
into the city and that's when I joined
the organization again. And so it had
lost its leadership, its staff, its way
in a lot of ways Um,
and the board members were all new. Um,
and so some of the challenges is this is
not operating the expectation sometimes
from the community is that this should
be operating like the good old days.
And the good old days administrative
budget is not what it is today.
And and so we're trying to make
adjustments of what we do and and what
we can do and do it better um, than
we've ever done it before and the grants
are super important to the private
sector and answering growth and that's
what we've tried to focus on cleaning up
those programs and putting out good
grants to good development projects
along with a sidewalk project that um,
I think the council um,
Mr. Leybourne was passionate about and
helped bring and create and that thing
is starting to get some traction and
we're starting to repair some sidewalks
um, and things like that. And so there's
an administrative burden um, to this
organization that isn't reimbursed at
the same level is what I want to say.
And so we're doing our best. There's
also a lot of pressure to be putting out
more money for events and a whole
variety of different things. So we're
trying to find that balance and some of
that growth is described in that.
Understood.
>> Sorry, I over spoke. Sophia.
Sophia Mayes, executive director of the
Downtown Development Authority. Um, in
terms of the reserves in comparison to
the fiscal year 2026, it does look like
a an immense amount. Uh, fiscal year
2026, we
budgeted um, to pull 224,774
from reserves and this year is obviously
434,000.
In the prior fiscal years, fiscal year
25, we had allocated 514,000
from reserves. In fiscal year 24, we had
allocated 784,000
from reserves. Um, this is a conver- a
bigger conversation that we're starting
to have with our board and
we actually had a work session this
morning about our our five-year
operational and financial plan moving
forward to understand exactly what our
North Star is, how we do want to
approach those reserves and versus the
larger projects for or programming
aspects. So, that's a bigger
conversation we're looking at, but from
the feedback we've had this last year
from a lot of different stakeholders,
they're not seeing the the fruits of
their mill levy and so we're trying to
put more out there and and make more
happen downtown this year.
Thank you.
Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins, through you. What is
after the projected $434,000 has been
out of reserve, what is the projected
amount that would be left
if this budget is approved?
Mayor Collins, through you.
The projected amount of reserves after
this budget would be by next July 1st
would be about $961,702.
Thank you.
Thanks, Sophia.
Dr.
Wallace
Did you have comment? What? Yeah, I
didn't. Okay. Mr. Mayor,
um
having been
a
on the DDA Council's representative of
DDA off and on a couple two or three
times over the years
and been there when when the community
improvement grants, the facade
improvement grants were first developed,
um, it was always viewed that those
funds would be dedicated
to help remodel downtown and improve
downtown.
And then to the landowners' credit, when
you know, they have voted in a a mill
levy on themselves
and I don't think when they voted for
that they expected us to the DDA to be
sitting on it and sitting in a bank
account. I think they expected that it
to be spent on downtown. So,
that I mean
so I don't think it's our role to build
up a significant amount of
reserves. I think it needs to be
reinvested and reinvested as
often and as much as we can.
And lastly, in in regard to the lack of
the location of the office,
um I realize there's a chance that they
may have to move out of here, but in
addition and perhaps
Mr. White as the council's rep or Mr.
Mr. Tubner as the president of the
board,
um
I do believe having served on the DDA
board when it was part of the city and
it was an independent organization,
I do believe that it is better within
the city. However,
I think there's been some pushback that
it the perception is it's too close to
the city
and I think some of the some of the
business owners would prefer to see it
not
co-located in the city offices, but
moved out and with being a little more
independent. So,
you know, I realize that on the surface
that may not look like a good
investment, but politically it might be
the right thing to do. So,
thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Anybody else in the governing body?
Mr. Leybourn.
>> [clears throat]
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. I also am a former
board member of the DDA
and was uh on that board at the
uh and very active in the
last election of that uh
mill levy. So, there's a lot of
knowledge there.
And when we look back over the years, I
I'm not really sure
when we started building up that
reserve, but
it's been there for quite a while. It's
been very substantial
and as I understand from the figures I
just heard from
Ms. Maze, um
we've got about 900 and some thousand.
So, even if
um
there was a uh
granting of that funds, which obviously
is got a lot of questions yet,
to the uh foundation, which is
now titled Downtown First,
uh there's still be uh $400,000.
My point is
>> [clears throat]
>> it is to the credit
of the DDA board over the years that
that money was saved up.
I don't think there's any denying of
that.
But, in the period of time that we're
living in right now and the improvements
to downtown,
I think it is very important
that this discussion we're having right
now
um of this
request for this $500,000, which is
um
certainly
unprecedented,
uh is an opportunity for us to really
take a look at that, to take a look at
the continuation
of the mill levy, if that's the choice
of the
uh
people who pay it.
But, really um
it's time to make a determination, and
I speak in favor of adopting this budget
with the
understanding that this is a
long, long time effort
that uh didn't have uh
the impetus, whether it was a grocery
store, whether it was a building,
whether it was a series of projects,
um
it there was a very substantial amount
of money put aside
that
is incomparable
to any other downtown development
authority in the state of Wyoming.
And we also have a downtown that is the
incomparable
in the state of Wyoming with the assets
that we have
of the Depot, the Plaza,
the various activities that we're now
seeing occur across the street here.
So, I hope that we can uh
note that this is a time of
really uh adjustment and we need to make
sure that
um
we take full advantage of that
expenditure. So,
I speak in favor of approving this um
with
the understanding at least on my part
that there's going to be some real
discussion here that involves not only
uh
the board, not only the council,
but and not only the people that pay the
mill levy.
Uh that interest in a uh
vibrant downtown is long-standing
and I think that it's uh
coming along.
I think that this amount of money could
do a lot of good uh to help that along
and I certainly uh
have a number of projects that I
uh believe would be appropriate. So, um
I think we should pass this
and uh
see what
this tremendous opportunity here of
these reserves can be uh
in in the in the near future
allocated for purposes that are very
understandable. Thank you.
Anybody else in the governing body? Mr.
Mayor. Mr. Wolf. Mr. Mayor, thank you.
Through you, um
I join my colleagues from Ward 1 in in
supporting this.
Um the the DDA is a unique organization
uh within the city.
Um and uh by the fact that we had this
outside board, we have uh
the employees housed and paid within the
city. Um
when I got appointed in late November, I
I just made a point of trying to to
learn more about it. I've been to every
meeting, I think, maybe save one. I've
been to all the work sessions. I was
there today.
I want to assure the public that um
all of the questions that have have been
asked tonight, the board has been
considering.
Um
the uh the questions and concerns about
the reserves were discussed today. Uh
the the office space,
um the relationship with the downtown
and with the downtown first
organization.
Um and the board is on top of all these
and the director and and her staff have
and I I think it's really it's both
fundamentally incredibly important to
the city itself and um and and I think
we have um
uh
it on the right path and Mr. Mayor,
I appreciate your support of that and
the chief of staff's support. Um
and um so I'm going to vote in favor and
I but I also have one question and I
first of all I want to thank President
Tubner for his so long standing support
and
other members of the board who are here.
Um but the one thing I heard of going to
the downtown first discussion is that we
need vibe downtown.
Uh and uh
and I and and as as
Mr. Tubner's in the vibe business. Uh
uh but one of the people who's in the
vibe business is Director Sanchez.
Um and um and I guess I hope as all of
us
uh enjoy the fruits of a lot of work in
the downtown, particularly over the
summer and Fridays on the plaza that
uh
some of the vibe for all of that is is
in fact the product of of the great work
of the board and of the staff and and um
and all of the integral parts um of the
city.
Thank you.
Anyone else?
So, it looks like we're all supporting
the DDA.
All right, we have a motion before us to
approve their the Downtown Development
Authority's budget as amended. All those
in favor, please signify by saying I. I.
Those opposed? The DDA's budget is
adopted as amended. And again, thank you
to their board members for their
service.
Next item is number 29A on page five.
Contract the City of Cheyenne and BNSF
Railway for a BNSF Railway and grant
applicant 22905 agreement for the Reed
Avenue rail crossing elimination
project.
All right, we have before us the 22905
agreement, which is the next step in our
ability to
do our Reed Avenue project. Well, it
talks about the elimination of four
intersections, 17th, 18th,
21st, and Dillon Avenue. And it talks
about our compensating the railroad for
the use of that right-of-way.
Ongoing appraisal that's going on today.
So, is there anybody in the audience
want to speak to
the contract with the BNSF?
Anybody?
All right, hearing none. Mr. Escobel.
Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
Finance Committee is to approve and I so
move. Second. Seconded by Mr. White.
Comments from members of the governing
body.
Mr. Laybourn. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um
I have a maybe [clears throat] Mr. Cobb
can explain
that with this
contract modification, our consultants
are going to be in detailed and
continuing
conversation with the railroad.
Does he have any timeline that we could
share
as to um
what he expects to come out of this
contract?
Mr. Cobb, any thoughts?
Um Mayor, through you to Councilman
Leybourne, not with this particular
agreement. Again, this is just to
support our FRA application. Um, but I
do have a schedule for you based on my
work session on Friday. If you'd like me
to share that, sir.
Mr. Cobb.
Make sure I say the same thing. I got to
check my own notes.
Consistency is appreciated, sir.
Mayor through you, sir, to Councilman
Leybourne. So, what we had talked about
was the 60% plan submittal would be
submitted August of 2026, sir. And with
a public meeting followed up in
September of 2026.
And then a 90% submittal anticipated for
February of 2027 to the BNSF Railway.
Mr. Leybourne.
Thank you.
Mr. White.
Thank you, Mr. Mayor, through you. I
just wanted to commend uh
Engineer Cobb and the consultants and
everybody who's just been putting in
all the hours on this. Again, um,
you know, we've made more progress
on this project
in the last
six to seven months
than we had in the last six to seven
years.
Fair.
So,
I applaud my colleagues who've uh on
council who've who've uh
maintained support for this. We're
finally starting to see
uh the light at the end of the tunnel,
no pun intended. And it's not a train,
right?
>> Yeah. Well, we hope it's a train. Yeah,
we hope it's not a train.
Uh and considering that these tracks on
a train only uses them once a week
maybe, um, probably not. But I just
wanted to thank my colleagues, staff,
everyone, uh, that's that's really
just kept supporting this project. I was
among you and and wondering if this
would ever happen, but it is happening.
And, um, I just thank thank you to
everybody's commitment.
Mr. Escobar, did you have a comment,
sir?
Nope. Okay.
Anybody else?
All right, we have a contract with I'm
sorry.
Oh,
Tina, I'm so sorry. I didn't see your
hand. Thank you, Mr. Laybourne.
We don't have the public public comment
on this one. Okay. Cuz I do have someone
with their hand up online.
Um, it's beyond the public comment time,
but, uh,
>> Okay.
Uh, who is it? Charles Miller. Course it
is. Go ahead, Mr. Miller.
Mr. Miller, you had a order of order,
but I'll let you slip in, but you got to
do it quickly.
Thank you. Can you hear me? Yes.
Uh, this is Charles Miller,
um,
for the record here. Um,
I'm I'm taking a look at some of the uh,
data that I have in regards to the West
Edge. And, um, some concerning things,
uh, came across my board here. Um,
so, uh, please just correct me if I'm
wrong here, but, uh,
uh,
>> [sighs]
>> I'm speaking today in regarding the
millions of taxpayer dollars and
specific purpose tax funds being
funneled into the Reed Avenue rail
corridor and West Edge development. This
council is treating the West Edge like a
cosmetic real estate flip while actively
ignoring the severe documented public
health and environmental hazards
currently plaguing that
>> order, Mr. Mayor. Is is related to the
I'm
>> I'm sorry, but this is this is in
regards to the to the exact area that
you guys are are um voting on. It's
that there's major issues with the pump
house wetlands, um which are immediately
adjacent to this project site. Uh this
body has discussed the involvement of
the EPA and the Department of
Environmental Quality due to
contamination plumes that have spread
toward town.
Um furthermore, your own personnel have
identified this exact area as the main
site of water quality deterioration
draining into the creek.
Um second, the toxic infrastructure.
While we are debating the aesthetics of
pedestrian pathways, municipal crews are
currently reporting that they are
smelling large amounts of hydrocarbons
while attempting to clean the storm
storm drains in this area.
We are um we are also tracking heavy
metal local limits for arsenic, cadmium,
and lead through the Board of Public
Utilities. Well,
City-County Public Health has confirmed
they're dealing with active cases of
lead poisoning. Now, I I'm not I'm not
exactly sure about that one, but uh
>> asked me to correct you if you're wrong,
and I'm going to guess you're wrong on
this lead poisoning one. The head of
that department sitting here right next
to me, and she's shaking her head no, so
Yeah, I I believe that's um
I pulled that from like a an older um
meeting the transcript that I was going
through.
Um so, sorry about that.
Uh but um
but but the other the other issues that
I had just raised were was is there any
dispute um on that?
Mr. Mayor, I think you're just
conflating conflating the issues. We're
working on uh trying to beautify a part
of our community and and bring back uh
buildings that are underutilized or not
utilized at all um that are 100 years
old and trying to bring um
retail activity and and business back to
those areas. Uh we don't disagree with
you that there are other areas that we
need to do, but it doesn't mean we can't
do both, right? So, I appreciate your
comments, sir. Thank you very much.
>> I just I just wanted to close with
saying that a functioning municipality
fixes its toxic infrastructure first. Um
and that uh that I believe that you guys
should freeze all discretionary spending
on the Reed Avenue corridor until a
comprehensive environmental
environmental mitigation sweep is
completed. Mr. Miller, your time is up
and thank you for for checking in with
us. Thank you.
>> Mr. Mayor. Yes.
I do want to point out that the money's
currently being spent and had that have
been spent on Reed Avenue were voted in
by the 2017
um special purpose option tax by the
voters and we cannot deviate from we
cannot spend it on any other
um anything else. So, we're doing what
was dictated by the voters of Cheyenne.
We all understand and know that. Thank
you. You know that apparently not
everybody listening understands that.
Understood.
Dr. Edmonds. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Mr.
Miller, I so appreciate your input and
your
thorough auditing. I'm not sure exactly
how that's happening, but thank you for
that. I would please once again ask you
to come visit with us down here at the
City Council and I would also invite you
to please call me directly. I am the
director of the Department of of uh
Cheyenne-Laramie County Public Health
and I would be more than happy to visit
with you about environmental health
issues in Cheyenne. I think that might
be really enlightening for you um and
help you maybe focus a little bit
differently. So, thank you.
All right, we have a contract before us
with the
Burlington Northern uh Santa Fe
Railroad. Mr. Laybourn.
Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Um
I think when you recognize Mr. Miller
out of sequence, uh that's a mistake.
Well, Mr. Laybourn, I thought maybe we
missed him during the public comment
part. So, uh that would have been our
mistake for missing him. So, it was an
opportunity for him to to get caught up.
I would say though
>> No, Mr. Mayor, it was an opportunity for
the spreading of incredible
misinformation.
>> True that.
That is absolutely
not true in any way.
This is a complex project, no doubt. It
has environmental issues.
It has uh
>> [snorts]
>> many
elements [clears throat] that aren't
directly related to this contract.
But this is not helpful, Mr. Mayor.
This is really confusing.
And if if Mr. Miller wants to uh
come down and meet with the staff or
meet with me
or any I am the chairman of the uh Reed
Avenue Steering Committee
and very involved in it. So, I think
it's a it's really um unfortunate
that this kind of misinformation would
being spread.
We This is a difficult project.
We're well on our way in in a successful
manner.
And this is just really really
not correct, Mr. Mayor, and I hope that
um
if Mr. Miller
wants to come down, he can. If he can
make sure he gets his uh hand raised in
an appropriate time, that would be good,
too.
But this is not right.
And and we really shouldn't be allowing
this kind of
communication
from someone uh
uh at home, I guess. Um I This is really
not helpful.
Thank you.
Anyone else on the contract with the
BNSF?
I hear none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I. I. Those opposed?
>> No.
The uh contract is approved with Mr.
Moody voting no.
Next item is number 30A, contract
modification number one to contract
number 8218 between the city of Cheyenne
and AVI engineering PC for on-call
engineering services. Dr. Rennie, this
is your opportunity for your conflict,
sir.
Mr. Mayor, my son is a partner in AVI. I
so I do have a conflict and I'm going to
recuse myself. Appreciate that. The
record will so show.
All right, we have a contract to help
our engineering with some on-call
engineering services. Anybody in the
audience want to speak to
this effort?
Hearing none, Mr. Escobel.
Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
fund
Oh.
Tina.
If it's time for public comment,
>> It is. we do have Charles Miller.
Mr. Miller.
Uh can you hear me? We can.
Every time.
Mayor Collins, members of the council,
Charles Miller for the record. Um again,
I just wanted to uh state that I am uh
looking at uh
a lot of data
um in in order to uh to to speak with
you guys uh
frequently as I have been. Um and so if
there is um
any issues with with that data um
in regards to it. Mr. Miller, do you
have a comment on this uh contract
modification with AVI? I'd love to hear
it.
>> it just if if there's anything that is
>> Mr. Miller, do you have any comments on
the AVI contract? Yes, um okay. So in
regards to the
uh it's contract number 8218 with AVI
engineering, is that correct? It is,
sir.
Um
so
let's see here.
Um
the city already employs a fully staffed
engineering department. Is that correct?
No, sir.
Um It's not correct.
What what's the level of staffing
there? We are short We are short uh
engineers in our department. We have
found them to be difficult to hire. And
so, sometimes we find ourselves
underwater with the amount of work that
comes in and we need uh some on-call
services to help bridge that gap with
our bandwidth.
Oh, um okay. Well, uh can the
uh can can either you or the or the city
engineer
um state on the record exactly what type
of specific design plans or construction
support services that AVI engineering is
providing um that the uh that the own
that your own salaried municipal
engineers are incapable of handling? Um
don't say incapable, sir, but we have a
bandwidth. Our engineers are very
capable of doing the work. The volume of
work is what's challenging us sometimes.
We get a lot of work that comes in at
one time and uh we don't have enough
bodies to do that. And so, we ask for
some contract help to bridge that gap.
Can the council provide the taxpayers
with an itemized list of the exact
projects this specific $25,000 will be
spent on, or are we simply topping off a
slush fund for future undefined billable
hours? Mr. Miller, shame on you, sir.
Um uh we just talked about this. The uh
uh
when the engineer finds himself in a
position where he doesn't have the time
or the bandwidth, uh we have a very we
have very capable engineering companies
in this community and we reach out to
them on a regular basis to help fill the
gap.
It's not a slush fund, sir. Shame on
you.
Thank you.
Anybody else?
Okay, hearing none, Mr. Escobedo.
Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
Finance Committee is to approve an
amount of $25,000, and I so move.
>> Second. Seconded by Mr. White.
Mr. Moody. Yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor,
through you. Um wanted to state again
what we had our finance committee and I
asked uh Mr. Cobb, if you just want to
tell the public this is also important,
too, for emergencies. God forbid a
bridge goes out. God forbid there's a
big pothole. Could you just uh enlighten
Make sure the public understands that
cuz this is very important.
Thank you, Mr. Moody. No problem.
Anybody else? I want to ask Mr. Cobb to
let the
public know how important this is. Yep,
thank you.
Ms. Laybourne.
Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Uh
I
>> [clears throat]
>> have concern about this contract because
of the
longstanding imbalance that we have
uh with this engineering firm.
It is uh goes back many years and as you
just pointed out, there are a number of
qualified uh engineering firms in the
city
that can propose on these matters.
And uh I do fully understand and should
note that uh this is not a bid proposal.
That this is not a matter of bidding for
professional services. It is uh a choice
that we make.
And we made this choice in the original
contract amount of $74,000,
which is $500
below the limit by which uh these
expenditures need to come to the council
and that they can be uh allocated uh by
those various departments.
So, we are now adding $25,000 to that,
$99,500.
And that's a very substantial amount of
money, Mr. Mayor.
And it is something that uh
was not offered to these other
engineering firms.
It was sole sourced.
And I believe that uh maybe Mr. Cobb can
explain to us
is this new contract amount of 99,500
uh going to be in this
the budget we're currently in?
And then there'll be another uh
situation in the next budget
for uh need for these services. Is this
uh
just in this budget?
Mr. Laybourne, maybe I can answer part
of that question and that is um we have
a number of these kinds of contracts.
Um we need help with drainage and we
have GLM and uh Kelly Hefner that helps
us with that. Uh we need some traffic
studies. Is it HDR and Stantec that
helps us with those um
um
those situations. Uh we have a number of
engineering contracts to help supplement
what we're doing. Uh ABI is not the only
one that we use. Uh we use a number of
these very talented local um
firms. Honestly, sir.
Well, Mr. Mayor, I think I've made my
point and I certainly
recognize that there are various
elements of contract uh
improvements or or decisions. We we just
passed one uh that was going to uh
increase the amount of money
paid to our consultants over on the Reed
Corridor.
This is a very unique and special area.
And and I don't believe I've got an
answer to my question. Is this
going to be in this budget we're
currently seeing
or is this going to be a continuing
effort? Mr. Laybourne, I believe it that
we're you're going to use the salaries
that are in the position of the um
the open engineering positions. And if
we can't hire those positions, we'll use
those salaries to supplement that. And
so in the budget is the salaries and if
we're not successful, we'll continue to
use their salaries to supplement with
the engineering contracts. And when
we're successful in hiring the engineer,
these will be reduced.
Well, Mr. Mayor, I think that uh those
of us that have been here for a while,
and I go back many, many years,
there is a tremendous imbalance
in the amount of funds
that go to AVI engineering as compared
to the other engineering firms.
And this is a very unique situation
where this is going directly sole source
to the AVI engineering, and being an
that original 745
didn't come before the council. That was
a choice that was made uh in the
engineering office.
So, I think it's a matter of uh
accountability, and I think we really
need to look and discuss this with the
other engineering firms.
And I really there is a there is a
problem here, and I just want that
noted. Thank you.
And I would like to note for the record
the
um the funding source on this, I think
is misstated. The correct funding source
for this is the 2023
to 2026 fifth penny sales tax contract.
So.
All right. Anybody else in the audience?
Dr. Aldridge. Mayor Collins, to you.
I just uh would like to
um
really have a conversation, quite
honestly, about
the um sole sourcing. I think that we we
as a council voted to increase that
dollar amount when the state did.
Um
which I believe is $75,000, and as my
colleague noted, this was done at
74,500,
so it didn't come before the council.
Um but in a time when there is such a
mistrust of
um
elected officials, and um a demand for
accountability and transparency, I think
that um when the public didn't have the
opportunity to
um
other vendors had an opportunity to bid
and the public didn't have an
opportunity to make comments on that
74,500,
for us to then
um go to an extension or a modification
um that takes that to almost $100,000 is
really unfair to the other
um
engineering firms in our community and
I just I feel like um this is a practice
that while it may be expedient and it
may uh work for the engineering office,
really doesn't work for the public um or
in our effort to build a relationship of
trust and and a transparency. So,
um I will be I will not be voting to
support this tonight. I just feel like
um
this is one of those areas that is uh
pretty gray
um
as far as my desire to um govern with
integrity and transparency.
Any other comments from members of the
governing body? Mr. Mayor. Yes, Mr.
Wolf. Um thank you, Mr. Mayor, through
you.
Um
Mr. Cobb can obviously defend himself
quite eloquently on why this contract is
necessary, but
uh let me just say as somebody who spent
a career working with professionals of
all kinds, engineers, finance uh
people,
geologists,
um
there is um there's a great deal of
value that comes with having
long-standing, trusted professional
relationships.
And I think at its core, that's exactly
what
uh Engineer Cobb is doing with this. He
has um developed relationships
with this with the consultants, the
individual consultants. They are yes,
they're at AVI, but it's really with
his fellow professionals that he can
pick up the phone and say, "I've got
this issue and can you help me analyze
it?"
And um
and and they know the city and they know
Mr. Cobb and they know the pressures
that he works under
and
um getting that advice is actually
probably the most cost-effective thing
we can do in the consulting business.
Uh and so I I think in the absence of
being able to really hire our own uh
people and not only hire them, but bring
them on and bring them on and give them
the experience that Mr. Cobb has, that's
a long process and we may accomplish
that, we may not, but we certainly don't
want to limit the ability of Mr. Cobb to
get the kind of advice he needs. Whether
or not the sole-source contracting
policies are the best policies is really
an I think an entirely separate issue,
but I would I would not encourage this
council to take a short-sided view of
this and I I'd urge my colleagues to
vote in favor of it.
Dr. Emmons?
Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um I'm going to
agree with my neighbor.
Um I think I I totally understand what
um Dr. Aldrich is saying and having both
worked in state government for a lot of
years and have been a lot of focus on
sole-source agreements and making sure
that things are above board and um
there's no issue of even a hint of
impropriety.
The trade that's obviously incredibly
important. The trade-off on that,
however, is whether or not we're going
to get things done at the speed of
government or the speed of business.
And I think that that's where we
that's where the the practical rub hits.
And I think
there are times we have to, as Mr. Wolf
said, give our
give the authority to the people who
know
who's who has the the ability and the
skill set out there and not hamstring
them for
re- I mean, $25,000 is a lot of money,
but it's also not a lot of money.
Um so, I I just would hate for us to get
things so caught up in bureaucracy that
we don't get things done that are
critical. And as um
Councilman Moody said, there could be an
emergency. I'm not sure about a pothole
emergency. I'm not sure what that is,
but there could be an emergency and we
do need to be able to be expeditious in
our efforts. So, um I'm going to support
this. Thank you. Thank you.
Tina, we're not on public comment
anymore. It's not a staff staff member.
It's not public comment. It's a staff
member. Mr. Barbour Bort.
TJ.
TJ. Uh good evening, Mayor. This is TJ
Barbour Bort, purchasing manager. Can
you hear me okay? We can hear you
beautiful. Thank you.
Great. Thank you. Um I just wanted to
just give a just another perspective
just so that we're all kind of fully
understanding how this contract origi-
originated.
Um
the engineering office does do a process
that's called the statement of
qualifications. So, for any consultant
in the region that is interested in
doing business with the city, they can
submit a statement of qualifications.
The city purchasing policy allows for
the city engineer and his staff to make
selections from qualified firms that
have submitted statements of
qualification for projects
up to $200,000.
So
the this contract that we're considering
was
a project originally
awarded for an amount that didn't come
before the governing body but met the
guidelines of the statements of
qualification for selection. But now
that we've passed the $75,000 threshold,
our city council process has directed
that the mod come before this body. So I
just wanted to kind of confirm that a
sole source selection really isn't the
right
nomenclature to use for this process and
that AVI does have a statement of
qualification record on file with the
city engineer's office and that's how
they were selected. So I just kind of
wanted to clarify that and and for any
other consultants that are interested in
doing business with the city to submit
your statement of qualification for any
future consideration. So happy to answer
any other questions you may have.
Thanks. TJ, thanks for the
clarification. Appreciate your input.
Dr. Aldridge. Mayor Collins to you.
I
I understand my colleague from Ward 2's
concern about the long time it takes to
do business with in government. However,
I don't believe that um
the
expediency
to do
to do things in a timely manner as a
business versus as a government
justifies
the lack of transparency. And $25,000
doesn't give me heartburn. What gives me
heartburn is when we get to 99,500.
And I think that that's where
I have a real concern. Um, I trust Mr.
Cobb completely and explicitly up to
$75,000.
Um, sorry.
I have my limits. Um, but at when we hit
that $75,000 mark,
um, I really believe that the people of
the community need to have an
opportunity to, um,
know and be aware, um, when we're going
to exceed that, uh, $75,000 mark, which
they have been through this
modification, but, um, it just feels a
little back door. So, for that reason, I
will still be a no vote tonight.
All right. We have a contract. Anybody
else in the governing body?
Hearing none, all those in favor, please
signify by saying I. I. Those opposed?
>> No.
Mr. Laybourn and Dr. Allister knows the,
um,
contract modification number one is
approved.
Next item is number 31A, consideration
of bid number S-19-26
for a contract between the City of
Cheyenne and Reiman Corp for the Storey
Boulevard Extension Construction
Project.
Wonderful. I see we have three of our
county commissioners with us here this
evening, uh, who are our partners on
this project. So, welcome, Commissioner.
Thanks for sitting through our meeting.
I probably need to do the same thing and
give you the same courtesy. I haven't
done that recently. Ours are a lot more
fun.
Mr. Mayor, members of council, um, yes,
Troy Thompson, Laramie County
Commission. Uh, just here to, uh, to say
we are excited to partner with you on
this project. Um, we're we're excited to
get this done. It's been a long time in
the, in the, in in the coming. Um, and
the county is, uh, willing to,
uh, you know, pitch in $1,161,510.60
to this, and we can certainly discuss
how we came to to that number. It's been
kind of a a long arduous process to get
there, and we can certainly, uh, discuss
that. I can ask questions if if or
answer questions if you guys would like.
Um, but again,
very much looking forward to this
project. Appreciate you being here. Is
there any questions from uh
from our team to the commissioners?
Go ahead, ma'am. Um thank you, Mr.
Mayor. Um as a new person on this, I'm
still trying to figure everything out.
So, I just wanted to kind of get the lay
of the land on how we got to this point
with the dollar amounts.
Commissioner, if you can answer that or
I can answer it from my perspective
later. Well, Mr. Mayor, through you
Excuse me. Excuse me, Commissioner. Um
could we put the map up, Mr. Mayor? You
You really can't talk about this without
looking at the map uh and and looking at
the different parts of it. Um at least
that's certainly what we heard in
committee. Um and um
Give us a a 30-second break here and I
see Jennifer. Thank you for your help.
I remember Mr. Cobby said it's in the S
drive.
Would it make sense to maybe take a
5-minute break so everybody can uh
maybe use the boys and girls rooms and
we'll we'll we'll come back here at uh
uh
how about 7:50?
Thank you.
Kathy, I love that jacket cuz I love it.
You can bring that on.
>> Right.
Um.
Thank you.
Have a nice evening.
You can't not do it.
>> All right, I'd like to call the meeting
back to order if we could, please.
Mr. Wolfe, we have a map up. Thank you
for that suggestion. That was a good
one.
Um
I think Dr. Emmons asked a question and
uh we were going to look to you, sir,
for uh your comments.
Mr. Mayor, through you, uh Dr. Emmons,
so
um from the county's perspective, so
this goes back many many many years. Um
we were approached by city staff um and
and the comment was made that we wanted
to to put this road through, and there
was a discussion about the county
uh being a party to that. And so um
we we said, "Yes, absolutely. I mean,
this has been much needed for for quite
a while." Um and at that time, there was
discussion about the county um you know,
we said if if we were going to pave this
road, we would um build it to a certain
set of county standards. And if the
city's going to build the road, it's
probably going to be a different set of
standards, curb, gutter, sidewalk, those
things that we generally don't do on
county projects.
And so um some some numbers came out,
and we looked at that, and we said,
"Well, okay. Well, if this was going to
be a county project, um we would do X,
Y, and Z, and the total was about
$640,000."
And the county said, "Well, we'll gladly
pitch in $640,000."
And then there was some discussion about
uh driveway culverts
um and the need for additional funds.
And so the county said, "Yes, we'll
we'll we'll go up to to $700,000."
Um and and then we kind of waited um
waited for the project to go.
Uh then there was discussion about a a
buried gas line
um in the county right-of-way, and the
discussion about how to deal with that.
And so in in discussions with our staff,
uh city staff, um with some work
commissioners, uh some councilmen, and
and the mayor, um we talked about
bumping the county's portion up to 900
uh $36,000.
Um and so we we begrudgingly said,
"Okay, fine, but let's get it done um
and let's move forward." And so then we
waited, and it didn't seem like anything
was getting done. And then we got the
latest numbers. Um and and again, this
is a very quick overview of this. Um
there's a you know, stack of emails back
and forth. Um, but but um,
then the latest we heard was, well, now
Laramie County, your portion is going to
be 1.6 million dollars and the county
said, okay, that that's enough. I I I
think we're out. Um, and and
unfortunately, we had the experience of,
you know, working together with the
Christensen Road Overpass and then with
Whitney Del Range. In Whitney Del Range,
we originally were going to be in for
770,000. Now we're currently in for 1.4
million. It's still not getting done.
Um, and so I I think the county said we
we can't do another one of these
projects. We don't have unlimited funds.
Um,
we we agreed to to get this to county
standards and and so that's the number
we came with and then um, Mr. Cobb and I
spoke at a ribbon cutting
a couple weeks ago and he said, can can
we please renegotiate that and and let's
talk but I said, let's talk about it one
more time and and the county commission
took the numbers from the 100% markup
and said, okay, if this were a county
project, we would do this, this and
this. [clears throat] We probably would
not do this, this and this. So, the
county is willing to put in what it
would take to to build this road to our
standards and that's the 1.161
million dollars.
Thank you.
Anybody else in the governing body?
Dr. Aldridge. Um, Mayor Collins, through
you.
So, in looking at this map, um, the dip
in the ma- the green,
is that to avoid the gas line that was
in the right-of-way? Is that why or is
that
is there like a dirt road already there
existing? Mr. Cobb.
Um, Mayor, through you to Dr. Aldridge.
Dr. Aldridge, the the what you when you
see the alignment diverting to the south
on that east side, it's directly related
to topography. So, when we originally
purchased the property from the Whitney
Geisel family, um, their ask was is to
is to take the hillside as well because
it would be a dormant parcel that would
be less. So, the alignment has to go
around an area that's it's a big steep
hill there if that answers your
question, ma'am. Thank you. And one more
question, Mayor Collins, for you.
Um I remember when we I went out and
talked with the Stone family who lives
at that intersection of College and
Story
and it was going to require a large
I want to say drop um onto
um
Summit that would or Story that becomes
Summit or whatever that goes all across
College um in front of their property.
Will this plan still require that large
um or leveling out of that large what
would have been that large drop and a
retaining wall in front of their house?
Mr. Cobb. Mayor, through you to Dr.
Aldridge. Yes, ma'am, there is a
retaining wall there which is one of the
items that the county did not want to
pay for, ma'am. But, um we did reduce
that wall height um to to minimize the
fill on that area. Thank you.
Anybody else?
Yes, ma'am. Um thank you, Mr. Mayor. So,
um
Mr. Cobb this probably a dumb question,
but if the green line didn't dip
and just went straight across, would it
not be cheaper?
Mr. Cobb.
Mayor, through you to Dr. Ramus. Dr.
Ramus, it'd actually be more expensive
because I'd be moving a lot more
earthwork or or modify or bring
earthwork from somewhere else.
>> Please don't do that.
Dr. Ramus, you can't see it, but there's
a pretty big knoll right there. And so,
we could spend a lot of money on moving
dirt or we could just kind of go around
it and uh I think that that was the
idea.
>> [snorts]
>> Mr. Wolfe, did you have a comment?
>> I did. Thank you. Why don't we go out to
the public first and uh and then we'll
do our comments after that. Mr. White.
Uh through you, Mr. Mayor. Mike White,
Laramie County. Um
through all the memories of the council
and the county
I'm a landowner that lives close to
there and I
Mr. Cobb's been very helpful for me um
to answer maybe a comment from uh Dr.
Edmonds.
One of the reasons I think was um
the road would go right in front of the
couple landowners there because that
road only goes to Highland right now and
uh
Mr. Cobb was intimate in working with
the Whitney LLC
and for many years um
this road
has been trying to be connected to
Whitney.
I spoke many times in opposition of this
because I'm a person that lives a little
farther north and a little farther east.
But as the discussions continued and
what the county was doing
and what the ultimate goal was to do the
Dell Range project,
I thought to myself, you know, if if the
people that live right there aren't
before this body um it even goes back to
when Councilman Cook was here.
And um
I support it today but cuz Mr. Cobb's
been very flexible with me
and very um knowledgeable to give me the
information and I commend the
commissioners. This is a
been a big project and project also
is part of the Dell Range project. So I
thank the the members today and I hope
you vote for it. Thank you.
Thank you.
We We have two members of the public.
The first one is Rodney Stone.
Mr. Stone, welcome, sir.
Mr. Stone?
You might be muted, sir. Yeah. Yeah, did
he unmute?
Okay.
Mr. Stone, go ahead.
Tina, why don't we skip him? Hold it
Leave him there and and we'll come back
to him and we'll do the other. Okay.
>> Who's the other person? Mr. Miller. Mr.
Miller, welcome.
Yes, sir, I can hear you.
Mr. Miller?
Just wait.
Can you hear me?
Yes, sir, I can hear you. Sorry, I I
think you jumped the gun on that one.
Sorry, sir.
>> I was just teasing you, sir.
Um
Okay. Um and this is actually
more of a serious one. Uh Mayor Collins
and members of the City Council, Charles
Miller for the record.
Um I'm speaking today to formally object
to bid
S1926,
and that's the $3.49 million contract
awarded to Wright Runyon Corp for the
Story Boulevard Boulevard
extension project.
Um before the committee attempts to
silence my microphone with another
procedural point of order, claiming my
comparisons are not germane,
let me explicitly place on the record
why I make why every point I make today
is strictly germane to this specific
$3.49 million contract. A municipal
budget is a zero-sum ledger.
Every dollar extracted from the optional
1% sales tax fund to subsidize urban
sprawl is a dollar actively diverted
from core failing infrastructure.
Therefore, questioning the fiduciary
prioritization of this specific capital
expenditure against our toxic lead pipe
crisis is the very definition of germane
financial oversight.
When we audit the audio from the recent
May Finance Committee meeting regarding
this project project, it exposes a
staggering level of administrative
incompetence and blatant developer
warfare. You're attempting to extract
$3.49 million to lay new concrete for a
private development and your own
admissions that the committee meeting
your own admissions from that committee
meeting prove it. First, let us examine
the 6,000%
traffic subsidy. During the May finance
committee meeting, city engineers stated
on the record that this dirt road
currently sees only 84 cars a day. But,
once connected to support the new
development, traffic will skyrocket to
5,200 cars a day. Mr. Miller, you you're
wrong. We did We never said it was going
to connect to a new development. There's
no development at this time. There when
we the day it opens, there's 3,500 cars
a day that will use this road. Uh I
think particularly county residents who
live in the eastern part of the
community. And then after after that,
when there is a
um
uh uh stoppage on traffic on Del Range
Boulevard from College Drive to Van
Buren, uh and we have to detour the
traffic, that's when it goes to over
5,000.
Okay, I'm going to go ahead and
continue. Hopefully, you guys credit me
about 30 seconds there.
Um
uh
What what
I'm sorry.
You threw me off there, Mayor. Um
Okay. Uh During the May finance
committee meeting, city engineers stated
on the record that this dirt road Okay,
uh at at that same meeting, Laramie
County Commissioners explicitly
testified that anytime a development
action puts 5,000 cars on a county
county road, they require the private
developer to pay for the infrastructure
upgrades. Yet, the city of Cheyenne is
choosing to pay
>> I agree with that, but it that's if
there's a development that causes
>> me to continue? Possibly so I can
continue.
>> factually correct, sir. And you asked me
if there's something wrong to to tell
you. There is no development that's
causing this. There's just pent-up
demand for additional uh right of way
and uh and for cars to be able to get
from the eastern part of the city in.
There is no development that is in the
county right now that would cause that
or in the city. There is just
thousands of River Ranch yet sitting
north of the town that are looking for a
more expeditious way to get into our
city. Maybe you could then tell me
why that when I asked in the May finance
committee meeting,
the previous one, that if public tax
dollars were being used to find a 6,000%
traffic increase for private real estate
growth that the committee's on the
record response was, "I guess you could
look at it that way."
Um the second, taxpayers are paying a
massive penalty for your for a
bureaucratic delay.
Um the county commissioner stated that
during that that same meeting that they
agreed to help fund this project 4 to 5
years ago, but the city failed to
execute causing costs to escalate. When
confronted at that meeting with the fact
that this 5-year delay could cost
taxpayers an extra $500,000, the
committee's only defense was a weak not
entirely. Third, you're actively
subsidizing private landscaping
preferences. As was confirmed in the May
finance committee meeting, the county
refused to pay for a $124,920
retaining wall required for this
project, correctly pointing out that the
wall only exists because the city made a
specific agreement with a single
property owner who did not want fill
dirt on his land. Public capital should
never be drained to accommodate the
hyper-specific aesthetics of private
landowners. When confronted with this
gross misallocation of capital in the
May finance committee meeting, the
chairman weaponized a point of order to
pre-
permanently terminate my line of
questioning without a vote using
germaineness as a containment strategy
to
>> Mr. Miller, get back to the comment,
which is this contract.
You're getting off the contract again.
Mr. Miller.
Okay, his time's up. Thank you.
Mr. Mayor. Mr. Escobedo.
Uh
it was called a voter by Councilman
White and second by Councilman Moody.
I was there. I understand.
>> not need a vote. Yep, absolutely. The
majority of the committee.
All right, where are we?
Okay, Jennifer.
Mr. Stone, can you try to unmute
yourself again?
Is that working? It sure does, Mr.
Stone. Welcome.
Hallelujah.
>> [laughter]
>> Technology, my friend.
Well, I don't do this hardly at all and
uh
I would be there, but I got a bum leg
and I'm just not very mobile.
But uh good evening, Mayor and City
Council. Uh Rod Stone here.
And the reason I'm chiming in is uh I
watched the video of the Finance
Committee.
And uh of course I've talked to Mr. Cobb
about this uh retainer wall in front of
the house uh
quite a few times and
uh but Troy Thompson said that uh the
only reason that wall is being built is
because of an agreement with uh
I apparently the city and a landowner,
which would be me.
And I just want to clarify that we do
not want that wall. We never have.
Uh Mr. Cobb is really dug in on it
though and uh
you know, first they were going to build
that road up 4 ft in front of our
driveway, which
it
gives us no access to the road. Now, he
he came out and he said, "Well, we're
going to go lower." and he held his hand
down. It looked to be about 2 ft.
But even at that, I think they're going
to have to do something wonky in our
driveway here, which I'm
I'm not for. Um
it
I'm with the county, you know, that that
retainer wall is um um
it's a lot and
I think that um
you know, when the county says it's not
needed, I say it's not needed. It's
causing us trouble.
That you could save the taxpayers' money
by not doing that wall.
And uh
toning it down a bit, I would like the
rise to start on the west side of my
driveway up to College Drive.
Which
it's about a 100 yd and as you look at
it, it's about a 6-ft rise in 100 yd.
It's very minimal.
I encourage you to go look at it. It's
it's not
you go to Story Boulevard and um
Powder House and you got a big hill
there right into, you know, the stop
light, but
um we don't want it and I guarantee you
if a little water runs off that road and
gets on my yard, I'm not going to go
grab a lawyer.
Um
it's uh
it's just a lot of lot of extra and it's
causing us issues and I wish that they
would redesign that, touch that up a
little bit to where
it doesn't have such a negative effect
on us.
Mr. Stone, would you be willing to let
them just do a slope then and um
and maybe have a little bit of that dirt
come over towards your property so that
they can stabilize the uh the road? Um
Well, not into my yard, no. I
Maybe they'll need a little bit of a
wall, but they're still talking 2 ft in
front of my place, so they're going to
take this wall a long ways.
And it's only a 6-ft rise in 100 yd.
It's very minimal and
uh
as long as they stay in the easement, I
don't care what they do, but um
actually, I'd like the ditch to stay
like it is because it water would run
off the road into the ditch and I've got
a 13-in culvert, it would flow fine and
there would be no issues. I think you're
spending a lot of money on that when
it's um um
it's causing problems and it's not
needed according to the county.
Thank you, Mr. Stone.
Thank you.
Anybody else in the audience?
You you stayed for this meeting for a
reason, didn't you? Welcome. I just want
to You know nothing to do today, so.
Mike Travis, uh Ward 2.
Um just a few questions. It's not to go
against it or
or for it. Um I have property on the end
of that road right at Highlands.
Mr. Travis.
>> [clears throat]
>> Um
my biggest question is I haven't got to
see the plans or anything on it. I'm
just curious
where the drainage ends up going out. I
I understand there's partial curb and
gutter
on that [clears throat] project. Um my
biggest concern is where it's actually
draining into.
Um I have a property that it we have we
you know we were in a drought situation,
but at one time there's cattails on the
one corner of my property. So at one
time it it did get some water to it. I
would just I just don't want to make
sure that the drainage doesn't come in
and
and actually cause any more drainage
problems in that area. So I don't know
what you got You guys done a drainage
study on that. Like I said, I'm not here
to
to put it down for or against it. It's
just the point of
Mr. Travis, I'd offer you two things.
One and well Mr. Cobb answered the
question, but uh
we actually have the final plans now. So
if you want to sit down with him and and
take a look at
>> can I can I'm pretty good at look
reading plans.
>> Yeah, so you can do that. [laughter] But
uh you could you could you answer the
question about the drainage study?
So Mayor, generally through you, sir, to
to Mr. Travis. So generally it it goes
where it went before, Mike. So we didn't
change anything. Um we we channelized it
and added pipes. Um the and the county
as part of this agreement is going to
install some culverts on Arthur. So,
it's going to come through that natural
area as it did before. Okay, so it's not
going to take it down further like
closer to Highlands or anything. So No
No, sir. It drains back to the at Arthur
just as it does now. And we're at the
culverts are added there and then again,
there's a there's a 20-ft easement on an
outside ditch that takes the water from
college to Arthur on that north side of
the road. Okay.
And then I'm assuming that that section
of Summit is going to be changed to
Story.
That far as the name. Are you going to
keep that Story all the way through or
are you going to have Story Summit then
Story? Mr. Mayor through you to Mr.
Chavez. Mr. Chavez, right now it it
stays named as it is. There is no This
is a This is a construction project.
Yeah. So, you'll have a
quarter mile there that changes names
and then goes back. Which is fine. I
don't really care. It's just curious.
So, it go it goes from College Drive
east it'll be Summit the whole way.
No, it'll be Story. Mr. Mayor through
you to Mr. Chavez. Right now it it'll
just remain Summit for the time being.
>> Yeah. Okay, so cuz you got Story coming
to College and then it looks like you
got Story on the other side of Summit.
So, for a few you'll just have a little
area there where Summit's going to Are
we going to name the city side Summit or
>> Mr. Mayor, just to be clear right now
there is no actual right away
established. It's simply property where
there's going to be an access road.
There is no name yet. Okay, so it's it
will stay cuz I just happened to look at
one preliminary plan and it showed Story
on the Whitney side. So, I just was
curious about that. It doesn't matter
for address wise cuz I think all them
neighbors there have a box anyways, a PO
box. So
it'll just be the UPS guys that might
have to figure out where they're going.
So
Mike, thanks for being here tonight.
>> Not a problem. Thanks, guys. All right.
Anybody else in the audience?
>> [sighs]
>> All right. Hearing none.
Um we'll go to Mr. Escobel for a motion,
please.
Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
Finance Committee is to accept a bid in
the amount not to exceed 3,493,630.85
cents and I so move. Second. Seconded by
Mr. White.
Couple things. One is um I think when we
look at the funding source for this, it
talked about using the '19 to '22 fifth
penny and the '23 to '26 fifth penny.
This project will all be funded on the
city's side with the '23 to '26 fifth
penny. Do I get that right, right,
Kylie?
Mayor, do you um
Mr. Cobb, can you confirm that? Is it
the '2019 to '2022?
Yeah,
yeah. I I thought we were '19 to '22,
not the the '23 to '26, Mayor.
>> So, I got it wrong.
'19 to '22 fifth penny sales tax. Okay.
All right.
Doctor, you asked a question about what
happened during the committee and maybe
I can just share a little bit about the
comments that I made during that meeting
and that was
um first of all, that this is a really
important project for the community. Um
there are lots of our neighbors to the
east that are looking to get into
Cheyenne and um
and and and using this road will take
pressure off of Dell Range Boulevard and
um and make that commute a lot easier
for a lot of our our residents
uh in the county.
Um there will be a day in the future
sometime when uh I don't know if that's
a decade away or whenever that um the
Whitney Ranch subdivision will come on
online and when that time comes, um
they'll be able to use this also and we
will file for reimbursement um for those
sections when they come on so they can
pay their pro rata share of this uh this
development. Um the bid we got from
Reiman was 3.almost 5 million dollars
and um
when the uh
we look at it, uh what I testified to
was the county's portion of this, if you
look at the geographic part of it is
1.465 million dollars and they've agreed
to pay 1.61 million dollars, which
leaves a shortfall of 304,000
dollars. And um
uh during that meeting, um our friends,
the five commissioners, called in uh to
talk about um maybe a little bit of a
historic uh
perspective of the uh of the road and
how we got to this point. And um maybe
would from my perspective um
you know, the timeline
you know, might be just a little
different from our perspective. We
finished this project in 2025,
and um the design, everything um
and and during that design, what we
found was there was a gas line, a
high-pressure gas line that was uh in
the the county section of the road. And
um when we went out there and we looked
at that gas line, we realized that the
gas line was too high for us to be able
to build this road as a county section.
The county section would have a paved
paved road, and then it has a ditch on
the side that that's the conveyance for
the drainage. Well, the the the gas line
would be in the way of that, and so we
could not build it. And um
so the the feedback we got was our
design included uh curb and gutter to be
able to control the drainage, and that
wasn't um a county standard, that was a
city standard, and that was rejected.
And um
so we had to go back and we had to
redesign the road. And and part of that
redesign was we had to raise the road, I
think it was 2 ft in order to be able to
get through it high enough that we could
build the uh
um
the the the proper drainage. And so that
took us an extra We had to go and we had
to pothole every piece of that um
um
that high-pressure gas line to figure
out what the height of that gas line
was, and then we had to figure out how
high we had to come up. And so that
added that year uh to the cost, and that
it had also added um a year to the cost
to the project. Uh I think the the fill
and the um the curb and gutter were
probably a wash when it came to cost
but it cost us a year and so that added
some money and um
you know I think fundamentally for me
what the what the commissioner said is
they should not be required to build
roads to city standards
that it doesn't make any sense and they
didn't want to agree to doing city
standards
um
I I look at it a little differently I
look at curb and gutter as an
engineering standard not a city standard
when you're in a situation where you
can't build a ditch you got to take
we're responsible when you design a road
that there has to be a way to mitigate
the drainage and so the engineers looked
at the situation that we had and said
well there's an elegant way to do that
which would be to put curb and gutter in
move that water along and and take care
of it the site conditions dictated what
had to happen which was the high
pressure gas line and I bring your
attention to our current project we're
doing which is Whitney and Del Range
why dot is doing that project not the
city and we have a similar section that
the county is responsible for and it
includes curb and gutter because that's
the the intelligent way to move the
drainage
so
we're there
some of the other things like adding
friction to the road
was rejected at the intersection of
Ridge Road excuse me College Drive and
Summit
the engineers were concerned that as a
car would accelerate off of Summit Drive
they might have trouble with the
friction on their tires and it might be
difficult to go across
College Drive which is a very 50 mile an
hour road and so they recommended that
we put concrete there instead of asphalt
because the friction would be
would be better
that was a $43,000
adjustment that was rejected and
again from my perspective that's not a
city standard or a county standard.
That's an engineering standard. That's
what the engineer said is the best for
this roadway is to make sure that our
traveling public, both city and county,
have the proper friction to to be able
to accelerate across the road going 50
miles an hour.
Um
And then that the comment about a deal
existing with a property owner, you
heard the property owner himself say
there's no deal.
Um and all the governing body members
here that were part of that
negotiation,
from my perspective, what I heard
and what I wrote down was
that um
I want to make sure I get this exactly
right. Um
that there was a
a deal
and that the the county commissioners
feel like it was a city's fault and it's
not their responsibility.
However, when that road or that Thomas
Heights was designed and developed, the
engineering plans were sent both to the
city and the county.
The city signed off on them and the
county signed off on them. And
unfortunately, the the design
was as successful as we'd like it to be.
So, this governing body spent hundreds
of thousands of our dollars to remedy
that fact.
We recognize we probably didn't have a
legal responsibility to do it, but we
felt like we had a
an obligation to do that. But, the fact
is both parties signed that and
you know, when it comes to um this deal,
I think we should both be partners in
doing it.
So,
you know,
I believe this is in the best interest
of the community. I have no problem with
the city council's decision to move
forward and pay for this. I am
disappointed though that it's been
characterized as we're imposing city
standards on a project when I really
believe that what's being imposed is
engineering standards, best practices in
engineering for this road, and that we
should have a more
I'm not sure the word I'm looking for, a
more even split of those costs based on
geographical location.
With that, I would encourage the
governing body to approve this
before tonight as it is in the best
interest of our community, and it will
become exceptionally important in next
summer when we do the the Del Range
project from Van Buren to college and we
close Del Range Boulevard, having this
detour will be so important for both
city and county residents.
>> Point of order, Mr. Mayor. Yes, sir.
If you're going to advocate a position
on this, you need to relinquish the
chair. Probably should do that.
Thank you. Anybody else?
All right, we have a motion before us to
accept the contract.
>> Yes. I I did have a question.
>> Please, sir. Uh
question through you to Mr. Cobb. Uh Mr.
Cobb, could you just talk a little bit
about this retaining wall? Um why it's
there, what it's used for, why it's
recommended. I just wanted to get that
um clarification based on what Mr. Stone
had had uh stated. Mr. Cobb, please.
Mayor, through you to Councilman White.
Councilman White, the simple answer is
we do have to flatten that road out a
little bit. We are talking about cars as
we as we indicated, it's going to go
from 84 cars a day, which it's an it's
at a right now it which seems like it's
not very steep. There it's 8 to 13% as
you depending on where you're at on that
little piece of curve. The road is not
crowned well. It it sort of drains to
one side. It is all gravel and it and is
fairly steep. Again, 8 to 13%. So, well,
I normally recommend no more than 8. We
we sort of found a compromise where
about 6.5%
if I remember off the top of my head
now, sir. And so, the fill in front of
his house is roughly about 1 and 1/2 ft
which we can mitigate. As you move
towards college it gets it gets higher.
So again cuz you're coming up to a road
at college much higher and it's it is
higher than the 6 ft.
So the highest part of the retaining
wall is in that area off of college.
Mr. Stone did not want any fill going
into any of his property. So that was
the onus for the retaining wall. We
cannot I can't I can't build a road up
to a standard without without actually
putting retaining wall in or allowing
fill to go on his property. So this will
all be within the right of way and
that's why the retaining walls are. Hope
that answered your question, sir.
Follow up, Mr. White.
>> No, sir. Thank you.
Mr. Wolf. Mr. Mayor, thank you. Through
you. Um
This has been an interesting
conversation and it was
very striking one at the finance
committee.
Um and
I don't want to exacerbate a conflict
between the county and the city. Um but
the there's clearly a different view of
the facts
of how this whole project has emerged
over the last 5 years.
Um
We almost sat in the role of a of a
little mini jury at the finance
committee meeting. Um and um
I I think just to simplify it where
we've ended up is that um we think
there's additional money that the county
should pay. We the city
think that.
Um
and you could take a
you could take a view that we're not
going to pay that, but I I really
applaud the
mayor for saying we need to get and the
city engineer we need to get this
project done done right done to uh for
the public benefit all at one time, uh
you could conceivably do parts of this
and um
address some of the cost issues, but
that's not the proposal in front of us
sitting here tonight. The proposal in
front of us is that the city is going to
pay this shortfall. That's what's
included in the uh motion of the 3.493
$630.
I'll forget about the cents.
Um
and uh
I I think from a public standpoint
that's the right conclusion uh and to
get this project moving forward, get it
done.
Um
you know, there'll be
times when we can argue with the county
about other things, but um I think the
conclusion is correct that this is not
one of those times.
Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Anybody else on the bid?
Hearing none,
we have a bid for Storey Boulevard
extension. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I. I. Those opposed?
This bid is unanimously approved, and we
thank you for your partnership. Thank
you.
Next item is number 32A on page seven.
Voucher report.
All right. Is there anybody in the
audience or on the governing body that
would like to speak to the vouchers?
Hearing none, next item, please. 32B,
announcement that due to the Memorial
Day holiday and city offices being
closed on Monday, May 25th, 2026, the
regularly scheduled city council meeting
will instead be held on Tuesday, May
26th, 2026 at 6:00 p.m. in the municipal
building, city council chambers, 2101
O'Neil Avenue, Cheyenne, Wyoming. Other
business.
All right, is there anybody here today
that would like to speak to us under
other business?
Anybody in the audience?
Online?
Let me guess.
Mr. Miller.
Mr. Miller?
Yes, can you hear me? Yes, we can hear
you. Um I I attempted to uh try to
to chime in on vouchers.
Um but I don't know you guys must have
I don't know what happens on your end,
but uh
>> [clears throat]
>> Um so
with the vouchers
um I just lost my notes here.
Let me see.
Okay, here we go.
All right.
And this is other business now, is that
correct? Mr. Miller, what are your
comments, sir?
Um
let's see here. You already wasted
almost a minute.
Well,
uh I guess that's my prerogative since
it's other business, uh but I am just
trying to filter through my notes here.
Um I'm directing my friends at God it
actually right now to item 32A, the
voucher report. This document is a
financial black box where the this
administration attempts to bury its
discretionary bloat and operational
hemorrhage. While this council cries
poverty when asked to fix toxic lead
pipes or maintain our existing street
grid, your own ledger exposes a
completely different reality. First, the
entertainment subsidy. You're actively
extracting $40,000,
uh which you just skipped over uh
quickly in this voucher. Uh but uh in
taxpayer capital to pay Far Out
Productions
for a Thanks for the Memories concert.
Taxpayer reserves are not a slush fund
for event promoters. You cannot extract
$40,000 for a concert while
simultaneously claiming you lack the
funds to comprehensively map and and
replace our failing infrastructure.
Second, the cosmetic consulting. You are
funneling another $12,292.50
to Lotus Engineering for a theoretical
comprehensive climate action plan.
Meanwhile, your own crews are on the
record smelling raw hydrocarbons in our
unmaintained storm storm drains. You do
not buy cosmetic climate reports when
your physical infrastructure is actively
leaking toxins. Third, the equipment
bloat. We are seeing 4,448
dollars paid to Rock Solid SST for
Q Works Flow 556K
suppressors for the police department.
We are told we cannot afford to pave our
streets, but we are buying thousands of
dollars in firearm suppressors.
Finally, the administrative bleed. You
are burning $833.40
on Amazon simply to buy flags for public
works. You are paying PEAC Solutions
nearly 1,000 a month to lease a single
IT copier. You are paying ALSCO over
$600 just to wash sanitation uniforms. A
municipal budget is a zero-sum ledger.
Every dollar you burn on concerts,
climate consultants, firearm
suppressors, and Amazon flags is a
dollar actively stolen from core failing
infrastructure. I demand that this
council reject um uh it's too late for
that. Uh reject the voucher report. Um
audit your own audit your administrative
overhead and freeze the
>> is up. Thank you. Yep.
Anybody else in the audience want to
speak to us under other business?
How about from the governing body? Dr.
Aldridge. Mayor Collins, to you.
Um I wanted to remind everyone that the
Boys & Girls Club uh breakfast, the Back
a Kid breakfast, will be held this
Wednesday morning at the um rack out at
LCCC from 6:00 to 8:30 a.m. Mr. Mayor,
it's tomorrow morning.
Oh, thank you. Thank you. The 12th. Yes.
>> The 13th. And the Council and Coffee
will be held on Saturday from 9:00 to
11:00 um May 16th at Eastside Dos Bog
for Ward 3.
Thank you, Dr. Ernie.
Uh Mr. White.
Just a reminder, uh sir, and unlike the
uh the previous speaker under uh the
public other business, I don't have the
uh chat GPT script to read, but I will
remind folks that um
the uh rooted in Cheyenne Spring
planting will be this Saturday. The
morning crews will be going out at 8:00
a.m. The afternoon crews will be uh
beginning, I think, at 1:00 1:30.
And I believe [snorts] there's going to
be a short ceremony.
Uh they're going to be planting their
3,000th
tree.
>> 2,000th tree.
>> 2,000th, excuse me.
>> Yes, sir. 2,000th tree, and um
I know a lot of folks on the dais know
him. Uh they will be doing that in Mr.
Don Morris's yard. Really? Uh I believe
that and I believe that'll be done at
1:30.
Wonderful. Thank you.
Dr. Emmons. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. I just
wanted to remind everybody that Saturday
Friday at L
Start again. at LCCC
our pinning ceremonies all day for
sonographers, radiologists,
nurses, that's in the evening.
Um speech language pathology associates,
PT assistants,
and also um preschool graduation, which
is very important.
Which is the best graduation, by the
way. It's wonderful. Um and then all day
Saturday our graduations from each of
the four colleges at um LCCC, including
the um
G what they used to call the GED. I
don't HiSET. HiSET HiSET HiSET. HiSET
um graduations. So, I would invite
everyone to come out. Um, you can get on
the LCCC website to find all of the
different times by school.
You're going to be busy that day, aren't
you?
>> Yes, I am. Mr. Wolf.
Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you, um, I
just want to, um, thank uh, Director
Sanchez, um, for
the Fridays in the Plaza, um,
tremendous, uh, announcement ceremony,
um, last week, and, um,
a, uh, exciting lineup of, um,
performances, uh, all through the
summer.
Thank you. It's going to be epic.
Marshall Tucker Band. Say it with me.
Say it with me. Marshall Tucker Band.
Switchfoot, yes.
Mr. Moody. Yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Through you, I just want to remind
everyone that it is National, uh,
Police Memorial Week honoring those who
made the ultimate sacrifice, and it's
great living in a community where we
support our great Cheyenne Police
Department, Laramie County Sheriff's
Department, Wyoming Highway Patrol, but
also for all of our law enforcement here
in the state and across the country. And
we definitely want to thank them every
day for ultimate sacrifice.
Thank you, sir. Well said.
Anybody else, Mr. or Dr. Rennie? Yeah,
Mr. Mayor, for anybody that cares, it's
two to two Avs and Wild in the third.
Let's go, Avs.
Okay.
Do you have a motion for me?
I do. Oh, Mr. Laybourn. Yes.
Mr. [clears throat] Mayor, pursuant to
Wyoming Statute
Section 16-4-405,
I move that the governing body meet in
executive session to consider or receive
information classified as confidential
by law. Second.
So, it's been moved by Mr. Laybourn,
seconded by Mr. Moody. All those in
favor of moving to executive session,
please signify by saying I. I. Those
opposed?
All right, we're going to move into a
very quick executive session. We'll ask
the team to turn off the microphones and
close the doors and we'll do this as
quickly as possible cuz we want to